<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Seaven sparkes of the enkindled soule With foure lamentations, which composed in the hard times of Queene Elizabeth, may be vsed at all times, when the Church hapneth to be extreamely persecuted. Drawne out of the holy Scriptures, after the forme of Psalmes. By R.B.P.</title>
            <author>Buckland, Ralph, 1564-1611.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604-1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4008</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117366</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852580</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852580</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17907</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17130)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17907)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1228:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Seaven sparkes of the enkindled soule With foure lamentations, which composed in the hard times of Queene Elizabeth, may be vsed at all times, when the Church hapneth to be extreamely persecuted. Drawne out of the holy Scriptures, after the forme of Psalmes. By R.B.P.</title>
                  <author>Buckland, Ralph, 1564-1611.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>156 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed with licence [by the English secret press,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[England] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604-1605]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>R.B.P. = Ralph Buckland Priest.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Selections --  Paraphrases, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17907:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17907:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SEAVEN</hi> SPARKES OF THE ENKIND<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LED <hi>SOVLE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH FOVRE LAMENTATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS, <hi>WHICH COMPOSED</hi> in the hard times of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> may be vſed at all <hi>times, when the Church hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to be extreamely</hi> perſecuted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Drawne out of the holy Scriptures, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the forme of Pſalmes.</hi> By R. B. P.</p>
            <q>
               <p>In my meditation breaketh out fire. <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 38.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Is any of you ſadde? let him pray: Is he of a calme minde? let him Pſalme. <bibl>
                     <hi>Iac.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 13.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>IHS.</p>
            <p>Printed with licence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17907:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17907:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VERY <hi>WORSHIPFVLL, MY</hi> EVER-HONOVRED Mother B.B. encreaſe <hi>of all good in him, who is</hi> the only good.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O</hi> many wee owe much, &amp; to ſundry their certayne due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; to friends, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, clyents, neighbours; to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructors, &amp; gouernors: but vnto our parentes we owe all; we owe our ſelues. Of which eminent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue although Chriſtians can not be ignorant, through the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent commendation thereof in the word of God, as which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne in the
<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 20,</note> ten Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17907:3"/>was by our
<note n="b" place="margin">Math 15.</note> Sauiours bleſſed mouth recommended; by
<note n="c" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> 
               <hi>S. Paul</hi> noted to be the first Commaundement, hauing a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe thereunto annexed: ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were the Heathens ſo deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of natures light, but that they alwayes held this as a high principle. The great reuerence of
<note n="d" place="margin">3. Reg. 3.</note> 
               <hi>King Salomon</hi> towarde his mother, is to be read in the booke of Kings: and no leſſe rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample had the Gentiles of
<note n="e" place="margin">Plut.</note> 
               <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obis</hi> &amp; <hi>Biton,</hi> who ſubmitted their owne ſhoulders to the draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of their Mothers Chariot.
<note n="f" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.</note> And the Apoſtle expreſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded children to yeald re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall vnto their aged parents; ſaying that it was acceptable &amp; commendable in the ſight of God ſo to doe. That ſame by way of <hi>Prouerbe</hi> drawne from the Storke, committed they to an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17907:3"/>care and memory: glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alſo at all times reciting that memorable nature of this bird, which is,
<note place="margin">Antipelar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gein.</note> that the younger fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth againe the elder, of whome before he was fed and bred vp. Let this litle labour of mine be in ſome ſort to play the Storke, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in a contrary, yet moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiualent ſort of foode; ſuch ſurely as in this time of my long abſence from you wil be as acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable (I doubt not) to receiue, as it was gratefull to miniſter it; &amp; ſhal prooue as cordiall in the vſe, as it was paynefull in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Liue you to God; who alſo preſerue you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Sonne with all loue and duty. R. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17907:4"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VOVTLY</hi> AF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FECTED, AND <hi>enduring</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HANKES ought vve alvvayes to re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der vnto God for you (DEARE BRETHREN) as worthy and meete it is:
<note n="2" place="margin">The. 1.3.</note> for that your faith highly encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, &amp; the charity of each of you towardes other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth: ſo that <hi>(other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>) glory in the Church of God for your patience, and faith in all the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, and tribulations
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17907:4"/>vvhich you ſuſtayne to an example of GODS juſt judgment, that yee may be accounted vvorthy of the Kingdome of GOD, for which yee alſo ſuffer. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt yee that our joy may be full.
<note n="a" place="margin">Phil. 2.27.</note> And be not in any thing terrified by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, what to them is cauſe of perdition is to you of ſaluation; and this from God: for aſmuch as to you it is giuen for Chriſt, that not only yee beleeue in him but that yee alſo ſuffer for his ſake.
<note n="b" place="margin">Epheſ. 12.</note> Yee were in times paſt without Chriſt, aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſtrangers to the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, hauing no hope of the promiſe, &amp; without a God in this world. But nowe are yee, who earſt were far off,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17907:5"/>in Chriſt IESVS become neere in the bloud of Chriſt for he is our peace.
<note n="c" place="margin">Colloſ. 2.13.</note> Dead when yee vvere in ſinnes God reuiued you together with him, imparting co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all your offences.
<note n="d" place="margin">Phil. 1.26.</note> Walke yee therfore wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the goſpel of Chriſt,
<note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 2, 15.</note> without reprehenſion in the middeſt of a wicked &amp; peruerſe people, among whome yee ſhine as lights in the world.
<note n="f" place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.11.</note> Be mutually comfortable, and edifie one another; as alſo yee doe.
<note n="g" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.12.</note> Yee haue not receiued the ſpirit of this world.
<note n="h" place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.2.4.</note> The day of our Lord ſhal come as a theefe in the night. But yee (BRETHREN) are not in darknes, whereby that day might as a theefe catch yee vnwarres: for all yee are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17907:5"/>Sonnes of light, &amp; Sonnes of God. We are not of the night, neither of darknes: therefore let not vs ſleep as doe others, but let vs watch and be ſober. Be inſtant in prayer, watchfull therein in thankſegiuing.
<note n="a" place="margin">Epheſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 18.</note> Be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebriate with wine, wherein is luxury: but be filled with ſpirit, ſpeaking vnto your ſelues in Pſalmes, and Hymnes, &amp; ſpiritual ſongs; ſinging and Pſalming in your hartes vnto our Lord, yealding alwayes thankes for all thinges to God the Father, in the name of our LORD IESVS CHRIST.
<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 14.13, 15.16, 16.23.</note> Whatſoeuer is asked in his name, it is obtayned. Yet
<note n="c" place="margin">Iac. 4.3.</note> ſome receiue not, becauſe they euilly aske. And commonly
<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> vve doe not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17907:6"/>knowe what we pray, as behooueth vs. But
<note n="e" place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.14.</note> this is the comfort which we haue to Godward: in that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we ſhall requeſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Not the Author: but ſacred Authority.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="Psalm">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17907:6"/>
            <head>AN INVOCA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF GODS AIDE, <hi>FOR CEASSING THE</hi> AFFLICTION OF <hi>his Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">THE FIRST PSALME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> MY LORD, O my God: how long wilt thou deferre the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of thy people?</p>
            <p>Ariſe, and free vs O Lord: ariſe (O Lord) and ſaue vs.</p>
            <p>Helpe vs thou in our tribulations: for vaine is the aide of man.</p>
            <p>Accompliſh gratiouſly, what thou
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17907:7"/>mercifully ſeemeſt to beginne: ſhewe forth the amiable light of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance.</p>
            <p>By the hand of thy great ſeruant IAMES, ſhake off our yoake: that we may finde him an honourable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter.</p>
            <p>Beautifie him with a name, more pretious then his Crowne: by the true name of a good King.</p>
            <p>Deſerue he the reſemblance of thy owne Title: <hi>Prince of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Leaſt they which vexe vs, exalt their hartes for euer: and magnifie themſelues, in their iniquities.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt tried vs, as the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond is tried by hammers: or gold in the fornace.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt chaſtiſed vs throughly for our offences: nowe ſpare vs for thy mercy.</p>
            <p>To thee lift we vp our eyes, who dwelleſt in the heauens: and ſitteſt vpon the Cherubins.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17907:7"/>
            <p> As ſlaues in their Maſters fury: or handmaides at their Miſtris feete.</p>
            <p>Attend from thy heauenly throne vnto our cry: for exceedingly haue we beene oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>Howe many are the dayes of our afflictions: when wilt thou doe vs fauour and bowe our Perſecutors vnto pittie?</p>
            <p>Thine we are, thy children and thy ſeruants: the ſcattered and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed ſheepe of thy paſture.</p>
            <p>Preſerue vs, for we haue embraced thy wayes: and diligently ſearched thy commaundementes.</p>
            <p>For which cauſe we ſuſtayne the note of folly, and madnes: and are a daylie laughing ſtock to each wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked perſon.</p>
            <p>Reputed alſo as vnworthy to liue: and enemies to our deare country.</p>
            <p>Our acquaintance haue vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne themſelues from vs: and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred our company.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17907:8"/>
            <p> Our friendes haue forſaken vs: our kindred haue no wil to know vs.</p>
            <p>Our brethren of the ſame wombe paſſed by vs as a ſtreame: vvhich ſtayeth for no mans talke.</p>
            <p>Swifter then Swallowes fled they from vs: for dread of the nets which are round about vs.</p>
            <p>They to vvhome vve ſhould be deare, deſpiſe vs: they which ſhould helpe, followe in the chaſe.</p>
            <p>Like ſole Camels in the wildernes are we become: like ſolitary birdes which haue loſt their company.</p>
            <p>Outcaſtes, of no body regarded: as broaken potſherdes were we trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder foote.</p>
            <p>At meetings men deuiſed againſt vs: at tauernes and banquets made they ſonges vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Neither ceaſſeth their rage to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine: that the milder minded drawe backe from perſecuting.</p>
            <p>Without committing folly are we
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17907:8"/>ſcorned: &amp; ſlaundred without deſert.</p>
            <p>Tongues are ſharpned againſt vs like ſwordes: malice is bent againſt vs as a bowe.</p>
            <p>Arrowes are in ſecret let flie to wound vs: ſnares are laied to intrap vs.</p>
            <p>The children of this world, ſeeke nothing more then our deſtruction.</p>
            <p>This their aſſemblies forget not: this is their buſines all the day long.</p>
            <p>Lawes laied they earſt for ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling blockes: &amp; croſſed thy edictes, the pathes of innocency.</p>
            <p>Beſet by them as thicke as bees: wee liue incloſed amideſt an armed hoaſt.</p>
            <p>They raged among vs as a riuer vvhich ſwelleth vvith raine: bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring downe the bankes vvith vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
            <p>Their inſolent fury as a flame: which catcheth hold vpon a pile of thornes.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:17907:9"/>
            <p> Oppreſſed thus by our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, we lay groueling on the ground: and by ſtrong hand were our neckes kept downe.</p>
            <p>Oh that at length they would not kicke againſt our litle redreſſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: for of the paſſed time who can record the calamity.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo, O heauenly Father: for it hath pleaſed thee, to compaſſe vs with payne and perill.</p>
            <p>Our bowels are filled with worme wood: our hartes long ſince inebria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with gall.</p>
            <p>To what ſhall I compare our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe: and reſemble the miſery ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares ſuſtayned?</p>
            <p>Our woes as waues of the Sea: our aduerſities as the ſandes thereof.</p>
            <p>Perſecution followeth vs, like thunder, and lightning: fire, haile, and brimſtone.</p>
            <p>More cruell are our foes then V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicornes: more outragious then ſwift
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17907:9"/>Tigres.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Dauid</hi> ſought to death by <hi>Saul:</hi> as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the bondage of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Suſanna</hi> in the handes of her accuſers: as <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lions Den: ſuch is our caſe, O Lord.</p>
            <p>Vnder vs is the appaling pitte: aboue vs the brandiſhing ſword.</p>
            <p>Within vs, feares: vvithout vs, terrours.</p>
            <p>No meane left to eſcape: but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thy diuine aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Were it not for thy great mercy: long ſince had we beene waſted and gone.</p>
            <p>Our Fathers ſinned and we beare their iniquities: but vnto howe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny generations will thy wrath be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended?</p>
            <p>Howe long vvilt thou ſhut thy eyes from the oppreſſion of thy poore: and banniſh their cry from thine eares?</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17907:10"/>
            <p> A greate ſpace haue our ſoules thirſted after thee: expecting the day of their redemption.</p>
            <p>As trauaylers in a dry &amp; vncouth way: as children weaned from their Mothers breaſt.</p>
            <p>Our hartes are repleniſhed vvith ſorrowe and heauines: to ſee thine anger ſo confirmed againſt vs.</p>
            <p>Hold not thy peace, but anſwere vs: nowe we lift vp our handes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy holy Seate.</p>
            <p>Conſider at length of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, O Protector of thy holy Church: looke dovvne from thy throne of Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Regard the daylie Sacrifices: and turne not thy face fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thine anointed.</p>
            <p>Iniquity hath preuayled: gotten the vpper hand, and proceeded with all extreamity.</p>
            <p>Becauſe of this we groane by day: and at midnight powre forth our ſoules in teares.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17907:10"/>
            <p> Memory of our tribulation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into our lippes, at table of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: and buſieth our thoughtes vpon the bed of our reſt.</p>
            <p>At our riſing it is in our firſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: at our going to bed we againe commend our cauſe to thy mercy.</p>
            <p>Diuers times in the day we bowe our knees: beſeeching thee at length to relent.</p>
            <p>Our eyes droppe continually vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Godhead: and our ſighes are euery moment ſent vp towarde thy throne.</p>
            <p>We haue put on ſackcloath and hayre: and humbled our ſelues in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and abſtinence.</p>
            <p>Girt our loynes with corde, aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our heades to the earth: and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied our prayers.</p>
            <p>Ariſe therefore, O God of hoaſtes ſtand for thy people: giue thy malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to vnderſtand, that their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are of fleſh and bloud.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:17907:11"/>
            <p> Heale the cruſhed and bruſed: ſet captiues at liberty.</p>
            <p>Thy might is not abridged: thy wiſdome is no whit diminiſhed.</p>
            <p>Make therefore the yron rodde quite to ceaſe from our ſhoulders: binde vp the woundes of the guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
            <p>Spare vs for thy name ſake, O benigne Lord: releaſe thy congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation from their affliction.</p>
            <p>Conuert the hartes of people to thee: and they ſhall be conuerted.</p>
            <p>Send forth thy grace: and put vp thy ſword.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt powred forth thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation like a ſtreame: and laide thy habitation like a waſte plotte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> hath ſtreatched out her hand, and findeth no helpe: ſhee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayleth her children, vvithout all conſolation.</p>
            <p>Nowe therefore ariſe, vntwiſt the twine of our tribulation: and breake
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17907:11"/>the exactors ſtaffe.</p>
            <p>Preuent the appointed time, O fountayne of mercy: abridge the dayes to the ſaluation of many.</p>
            <p>If thouſandes wilfully run aſtray: yet thouſandes finde their ruine by ignorance.</p>
            <p>Moſt part of this harueſt periſheth for wante of reaping: though much be blighted before the ſickle.</p>
            <p>Many which ſhined in thy church like ſtarres: are fallen as from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, into the bottomeleſſe pit.</p>
            <p>Many bredde vp in thy fragrant garden: vvallowe novve vvithout doores vpon filth with ſwine.</p>
            <p>Whome thy Spouſe foſtered vp with her owne breaſtes: thoſe haue ſauage beaſtes raught from betweene her armes, and deuoured.</p>
            <p>So that ſhee is become as a tree blaſted: and caſting her bloſſomes with the froſt.</p>
            <p>Her faire ones are altered to <hi>Aethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians:</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17907:12"/>her ſtronge ones changed to weakelinges.</p>
            <p>They which ſeemed ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt haue ſhrunke vnder the burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they which ſeemed ſoundeſt are conſumed.</p>
            <p>Hell hath widned his entrailles: and opened his mouth beyond all meaſure.</p>
            <p>So that almoſt as many ſoules are ſwallowed in his gulfe: as bodies are carried to the graue.</p>
            <p>The fainter ſort are tyred in this long probation: &amp; blaſpheamouſly ſay in their hartes, where is our God become?</p>
            <p>Scarce the juſt &amp; elect haue beene able to endure: Reſpect therefore at laſt (O Lord) our oppreſſion &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
            <p>For thy loue and for defence of our faith it is: that we haue taken ſo hard a courſe.</p>
            <p>For righteouſnes we ſuſtayne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe: for not violating our allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17907:12"/>to thy ſoueraigne Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Who art the only Lord of Lordes: and Monarch of the whole world.</p>
            <p>Before whoſe face the mountayns tremble: &amp; to whome Angels bowe.</p>
            <p>Whoſe ſlaues and vaſſals: are all the Princes of the earth.</p>
            <p>When thou liſt thou pluckeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their chaynes of gold: and tieſt a rope about their neckes.</p>
            <p>For thy ſeruice we ſuffer, hating the profane Church: and refuſing to ſit in the congregation of the wicked.</p>
            <p>Vngodly aſſemblies we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted: and held in abhomination the Doctrine of the chaire of peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
            <p>Conceale therefore no longer our innocency: the mouth of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is opened againſt vs.</p>
            <p>And that without our fault, thou knoweſt: who quietly ſeeke to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our liues.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:17907:13"/>
            <p> They ſay to vs, talke not of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: meddle not of Religion and you ſhall be free.</p>
            <p>Yeald to vs in ſhewe: and giue outward conſent to our lawes and actions.</p>
            <p>Come reuerently to our rites, and prayers: be one of vs, at leaſt in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
            <p>Forſake your accuſtomed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: renounce the ſociety and communion of Catholikes.</p>
            <p>Then beleeue in hart howe you lift: we admit you good ſubjectes, and no enemies of our Religion.</p>
            <p>Miſery hangeth ouer our heads, if we yeald not to this ſuggeſtion: but a thouſand miſeries if we doe relent.</p>
            <p>If we forſake thy Tabernacle, hell claymeth intereſt in vs: the fiend ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſeyzion of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Standing ſtedfaſt vve are conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to nothing: neither finde end of trouble but by death.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="Psalm">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:17907:13"/>
            <head>A CONSOLATORIE <hi>PSALME, ANSWE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> to the former.</head>
            <head type="sub">THE SECOND PSALME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>IFT vp thy head, O Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Sion:</hi> receiue comfort, yee children of <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> Yee zealous ſoules, who groane vnder ſore perſecution: and ſit in heauines for your conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>Who haue beene tried by fire, and found pure: peyſed in ballance, and found ſufficient.</p>
            <p>Your conſtancy our Lord &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker hath beheld: accepting the ſame as a moſt gratefull Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>Confirme your hartes in hope: for your redemption is not farre off.</p>
            <p>The yeare of viſitation draweth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17907:14"/>to an end: and Iubilation is at hand.</p>
            <p>Albeit yee be as drops fallen into the Sea: and as graines of gold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the mountaynes.</p>
            <p>Yet are yee reſpected from on high as loyall, and louing children: the reliques of <hi>Iſraell</hi> ſhall bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> ſhall be built vp againe: and the ſecond glory thereof ſhal be greater then the firſt.</p>
            <p>The Church purged in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of tribulation: ſhal ſhine brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then euer before.</p>
            <p>Righteouſnes ſhall proſper: and infidelity ſhall bee plucked vp by the rootes.</p>
            <p>God wil ariſe, as from a long ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: and eſtabliſh againe the Arke of his ſanctification.</p>
            <p>Feare not, little IACOB: hee that is thy Redeemer from the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, will be thy deliuerer from all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17907:14"/>euill.</p>
            <p>His thou art, his flocke and fold: Catholike is thy name.</p>
            <p>To hurt thee, is to hurt him: to touch thee, is to touch the apple of his eye.</p>
            <p>Ariſe therefore from the earth, ſhake off ſorrowes: thy confuſion ſhall giue glace to glory.</p>
            <p>The morning dewe is preſt to fal: and the night to be diſcharged of her courſe.</p>
            <p>With the eye of pitty the Lord of hoſtes ſhall viſit vs: and ſend ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his people.</p>
            <p>Turning their water into wine: their wormewood into ſuger canes.</p>
            <p>His ſcattered flocke he will vnite againe: and reduce ſtrayers into ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>The roote which hath waxen old vnder ground, ſhall ſhoote vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: as a freſh plant by the riuer ſide.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17907:15"/>
            <p> No man ſhall vpbraid it vvith barrennes: or ſay it vvas a curſed ſtocke.</p>
            <p>Falſe errour ſhall vaniſhe like ſmoake: and they vvhich ſawe it ſhall ſay, where is it become?</p>
            <p>Iuſt judgement and holy lawes: ſhall be reſtored.</p>
            <p>If a Woman can forget her child, or if we can forget our right handes: yet will not Chriſt be vnmindfull of <hi>Sion</hi> his heritage.</p>
            <p>Sooner ſhall he forget his owne throne: then her deſolation.</p>
            <p>For aſhes, hee ſhall giue her a Crowne: for baths of teares, vnction of joy.</p>
            <p>Requiting her ignominy with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: her ſackcloath of ſorrowe with robes of feſtiuity.</p>
            <p>His Tabernacle he will ſpred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: and dwell among vs as in time paſt.</p>
            <p>Cladding his Prieſtes with holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17907:15"/>and his ſeruants with purity.</p>
            <p>Sacred ſonges ſhall breake their long ſilence: the lampe of our Lord ſhall be reuiued.</p>
            <p>Preachers of ſaluation: ſhall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare lift vs their voice.</p>
            <p>The Churches ſhall be hallowed againe: &amp; no vncleane perſons ſhall enter therein.</p>
            <p>The forreſts and rockes ſhal ſend thither their chiefeſt glory: for beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of ſacred workes.</p>
            <p>Screetch-owles ſhall ſeeke newe habitation: and reſigne to the ſimple Doue.</p>
            <p>With ſweeter then milke &amp; hony: ſeauen fountaynes ſhal ſpring afreſh, and flowe.</p>
            <p>The reſemblance of heauen ſhall be renewed: the reſemblance of hell ſhall be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> ſhall bee called a happy Realme: a bleſſed Country, a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious people.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17907:16"/>
            <p> Thoſe which knewe the former glory of Religion: ſhall lift vp their handes for joy, to ſee it returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <p>Thoſe which neuer ſawe it: ſhall be ſtroaken with admiration.</p>
            <p>VViſhing that they had ſooner knowne the truth: and condemning their fathers, which forſooke it.</p>
            <p>Men ſhal ſay of it one to another: here is indeede the houſe of God, &amp; the gate of heauen.</p>
            <p>Howe great diuerſity is betweene truth, and falſhoode: deuout ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities, and counterfeit ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies?</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Eaſt</hi> point to the <hi>Weſt:</hi> men ſhall confeſſe their errours.</p>
            <p>They which thought themſelues wiſeſt: ſhall ſay they knew nothing.</p>
            <p>Gladly ſhall people walke in their auncients ſteps of truth and equity: beginning to learne howe to loue God aright.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:17907:16"/>
            <p> Howe to loue him, and ſerue him: howe to honour him ſincerely in a perfect hart.</p>
            <p>Be no more apald, O little flocke of Chriſt: the Prince of peace vvill breake the exactors rodde.</p>
            <p>Reſcuing you from captiuity: and bringing you vnto deſirable paſtures</p>
            <p>Take courage for he is with you: his aſſiſtance neuer faileth.</p>
            <p>To his glory he created you: and for his name ſake he wil protect and ſaue you.</p>
            <p>No longer will he diſſemble the oppreſſion of his people: he is bent to reuenge their cauſe.</p>
            <p>The Daughters of <hi>Babilon</hi> ſhall be caſt downe: and in the duſt lament their ruine.</p>
            <p>Proude Hereſie ſhall ſtrike her ſaile: and groane as a beaſt, cruſhed vnder a cartwheele.</p>
            <p>Though her hart be flint: her neck yron, her forhead braſſe.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17907:17"/>
            <p> The Omnipotent hath ſworne to make her ſtoope: and that he vvill abaſe her haughtines.</p>
            <p>Though ſhee fret his choſen vine neuer ſo much: in deſpight of her it ſhall ſhoote vp and proſper.</p>
            <p>Ten times if it be cut downe: ten times it ſhall ariſe more glorious.</p>
            <p>God hath planted it with his owne hand: he hath vvatered it vvith the bloud of Martirs, &amp; it ſhall flouriſh.</p>
            <p>He hath conſidered the inſolency of our enemies: their cruell dealing hath not eſcaped his ſight.</p>
            <p>Howe arrogantly they walke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our face: glorying in their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes.</p>
            <p>But the memory of nouelties ſhall periſh with a cracke: as a ruinous houſe falling to the ground.</p>
            <p>Repent yee ſeducers with ſpeede: and preuent the dreadfull wrath of the moſt powreable.</p>
            <p>Leaſt his ire tread vpon you: like
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17907:17"/>a conquerour.</p>
            <p>Leaſt ſodainely he draw you forth out of your terreſtriall Paradiſe: as thornes, vvhich are not pulled vp with handes.</p>
            <p>We haue long taſted the cup of his indignation: but for ſinners he hath reſerued the dregges thereof.</p>
            <p>Greene and flouriſhing boughes haue not eſcaped his heauy hand: and ſhall he be mercifull to rotten branches?</p>
            <p>Let iniquity no longer lie: decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it ſelfe with vaine ſecurity.</p>
            <p>For thus promiſeth the defendor of <hi>Iſraell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He will come as a flame: that bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth out beyond the fornace.</p>
            <p>His enemies, ſhall be like ſtubble in his way.</p>
            <p>His fury ſhal flie forth as thunder: and pitch vpon their tops, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne him.</p>
            <p>With him, is both wiſdome and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17907:18"/>ſtrength: he quaileth the world with a becke.</p>
            <p>He knoweth how to dull the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of the mighty: and to fruſtrate the counſaile of the ſage.</p>
            <p>He buildeth, &amp; breaketh ſcepters: and bringeth wiſardes to their wittes end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharao</hi> was by his plagues compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: to let the children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice in liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyrus</hi> by his aide conquered the <hi>Oppreſſor:</hi> &amp; diſſolued by his inſtinct, the long captiuity of <hi>Iuda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond <hi>Cyrus</hi> hath he ſtirred vp: confirming his ſcepter for the good of his people.</p>
            <p>He ſhal likewiſe bring the Infants of <hi>Sion,</hi> from all quarters of their ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: joyfully ſhall they returne from forraigne landes.</p>
            <p>And thoſe Countries where now they harbour: ſhall finde ſuccour in this Iſle to their ovvne neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:17907:18"/>
            <p> Thriſe happy are yee who ſhall ſee thoſe dayes: your hartes ſhall be repleniſhed with joy.</p>
            <p>There ſhal not be any more grief: miſery, and tribulation.</p>
            <p>But perſecution ſhal be recoump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with mirth: as perſons arriued diſcourſe of ſhipwracke.</p>
            <p>The arme of the malignant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing broaken: our LORD ſhall raigne in mens hartes, for euer and euer.</p>
            <p>The tempeſtuous night being paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: a perpetuall day ſhall be our comfort.</p>
            <p>Which if we liue to ſee: to haue ſuffered for Chriſt, ſhall be a joy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring life.</p>
            <p>If we die before: we reſt in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red confidence, of a happy reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>And alwayes an immaculate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ſhall bee a ſvveete odour
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17907:19"/>to the Almighty: and a banquet to our ſelues.</p>
            <p>By affliction our ſoules are pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of their droſſe: and their imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections conſumed.</p>
            <p>By perſecution we are tried as by the fanne: whether we will be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with euery wind.</p>
            <p>They which nowe ſtand ſhall be planted afreſh, as a glorious genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and be as principall ſtones in reſtauration of the Temple.</p>
            <p>Aboundantly ſhall Gods mercies recompence their loſſes: gladneſſe ſhal exceede their ſorrowes an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred-fold.</p>
            <p>All that ſhall ſee them ſhall know and ſay: theſe are they which would not bowe to <hi>Baall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſtant Confeſſors of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: &amp; the only glory of our nation.</p>
            <p>Iuſt is God in his judgementes: and hath ordayned a time, wherein to remember vs.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:17907:19"/>
            <p> His comming ſhall be as a ſweete ſhowre to the parched ground: and as a labourers vvages at the vveekes end.</p>
            <p>Ceaſe ſhall our bondage: and he ſhall bleſſe vs vvith an eternall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            <p>His truth, his juſtice, his Prieſtes, his Sacrifice: ſhal no more be taken away.</p>
            <p>For a moment he afflicted vs: but for euer ſhall his conſolation endure.</p>
            <p>Nowe therefore ſhew your ſelues men: yee that endure for juſtifying your faith.</p>
            <p>Runne forward without wearines: atchieue vvithout fainting a happy courſe.</p>
            <p>A Crowne hangeth ouer your heades: vnſpeakeable bliſſe is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for you.</p>
            <p>God himſelfe ſhall be your great reward: your hope is full of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="Psalm">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:17907:20"/>
            <head>A DEEPE RECOGITA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, <hi>OF THE FIRST</hi> conuerſion of the Engliſh <hi>nation to the faith of Chriſt, and the continuance thereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">THE THIRD PSALME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y hart melteth, and my bowels tremble: while I conferre the times, O my God.</p>
            <p>The times of this our miſerable age: with the golden dayes of our forefathers.</p>
            <p>We haue heard with our eares: and thy Scribes haue commended to eternall memory.</p>
            <p>The worke that thou wroughteſt one thouſand yeares paſt: in conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Aunceſtors to the faith.</p>
            <p>To a people that ſate in darkneſſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17907:20"/>and ſhadowe of death: it pleaſed thee to ſhew the light of thy countenance.</p>
            <p>That the reliques of an Heathen nation ſhould be ſaued: that no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould be exempt from know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy lawe, and title to thy glory.</p>
            <p>Thou preparedſt thine elect ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Gregory:</hi> to gouerne the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike Sea.</p>
            <p>A Paſtor like <hi>Dauid:</hi> according to thine owne hart.</p>
            <p>Who vvith great care executing his charge: fulfilled perfectly the name and office of a watchman.</p>
            <p>Thou ſtirredſt vp his hart: to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe the conuerſion of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And enflamedſt his minde: with zeale of dilating thy name vnto the endes of the world.</p>
            <p>While he was yet priuate: thou hadſt ſent of our youth to be ſold at <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:17907:21"/>
            <p> Intending thereby: the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of thy purpoſed mercy.</p>
            <p>They were brought to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-place, to be cheapned as beaſtes: price was ſet vpon them as ſlaues.</p>
            <p>Endevved yet vvith reaſonable ſoules, and ſuch viſages: as commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the excellency of thy beautifull workmanſhip.</p>
            <p>Iuſt neuertheleſſe was their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition: vvho vvere bruite beaſtes by ſinne, and ſlaues of the Diuell by infidelity.</p>
            <p>Thy holy ſeruant ſawe them: and his hart yearned at their calamity.</p>
            <p>But thou inſpiredſt him that their ſaluation was neare: and that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould be the inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thereof.</p>
            <p>Thou placedſt thy wordes in his lips: and hearing that they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Angles,</hi> he ſaid.</p>
            <p>To Angels this nation muſt be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited: whome in countenance they ſo reſemble.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:17907:21"/>
            <p> Vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding their Prouince was called <hi>Deira:</hi> and their King <hi>Aëlle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He inferred, that deliuered from Gods ire &amp; indignation: they ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould ſing <hi>Alleluia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this (O Lord) thou diddeſt raiſe vp <hi>Gregory:</hi> to be ſupreame Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor of thy vniuerſall flocke.</p>
            <p>Thou gaueſt him both ability and will: to compaſſe that which he had before thirſted.</p>
            <p>And to finiſh the worke: which thou ſecretly hadſt in hand.</p>
            <p>He ſent <hi>Auguſtine</hi> thy approoued Prieſt: with a choſen company, fit for ſo great and holy an enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>A long and weary ſome way they paſſed: but thou eaſedſt their trauaile with daylie conſolation.</p>
            <p>In the midſt of their journey their courage languiſhed: but thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmedſt them afreſh.</p>
            <p>Through ſtraunge landes, and vncouth wayes they paſſed: but thy
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17907:22"/>hand euermore protected them.</p>
            <p>They croſſed the Seas: and came to an Iſland, whoſe tongue they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not.</p>
            <p>Thou dideſt alwayes aſſiſt them: and wert a preſent aide to their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities.</p>
            <p>Thou art Lord of the Iſles, no leſſe then of the continent: neither doth diſtance of places abridge thy power.</p>
            <p>Thus thou broughteſt Monkes from beyond the high &amp; inſuperable <hi>Alpes:</hi> to kindle in Infidels hartes the fire of thy loue.</p>
            <p>At their entrance they bare before them the triumphant ſigne of the Croſſe: the badge of Chriſtians, the memory of our Redemption.</p>
            <p>A token that they preached the Sonne of Man crucified: a proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their faith, and profeſsion.</p>
            <p>They ſange the ſacred Litanies with loude voice: inuocating Saints
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17907:22"/>and Angels to their aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Grace thou gaueſt them in the ſight of Princes: and our Country beganne to yeald her fruits.</p>
            <p>The ſeede vvhich they ſovved tooke roote: and yealded encreaſe apace.</p>
            <p>Through many tempeſtes, and ſtormes it preuailed: through con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions it augmented the more.</p>
            <p>They conquered this land to thy CHRIST: and ſubdued all mens hartes to thy Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Poſſeſſing the Prouinces not by the ſword, but in thy word: not in their arme, but in thy ſpirit.</p>
            <p>They eſtabliſhed the function of thy holy Altar: wherein thy Sonne is both Prieſt and Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>They adminiſtred the ſeauen SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRAMENTES: and planted the vvhole Doctrine of the Catholike Church.</p>
            <p>They laide a firme foundation
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17907:23"/>of their forefathers faith: with the honourable rites thereunto apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning.</p>
            <p>And once more this Iſland flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed afreſh: recouering her aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient glory.</p>
            <p>Which many yeares before ſhee had attayned: by embracing the Chriſtian faith.</p>
            <p>Vaunting her ſelfe to be the firſt Chriſtian Prouince of the world: the eldeſt child of the Church.</p>
            <p>The faithful throughout the earth: rejoyced at her Religious example.</p>
            <p>Singing her happy choice, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrating her with Titles: ſome of Chriſts birth-right, ſome of our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies dowry.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Lucius</hi> by thy ſecret motion: inclined his hart to ſearch thy truth.</p>
            <p>Animated by thee (O Soueraigne Sanctifier) to <hi>Rome</hi> as the fountayne he ſent for water of life.</p>
            <p>Thy high Steward &amp; Lieutenant
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17907:23"/>
               <hi>Eleutherius:</hi> aſſigned Prieſts for exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his holy deſires.</p>
            <p>The light of thy word was ſoone ſpred through <hi>Britaine:</hi> to the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many ſoules.</p>
            <p>The Prophecy was ſo fulfilled: that from the Iſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds our Lord ſhould beginne his raigne.</p>
            <p>In this thy garden grewe vvhite Lillies without number: and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of life adorned the Realme.</p>
            <p>But neither was the red Roſe wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: purpled with the bloud of thy Saintes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alban</hi> the Prothomartir: for har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring a Prieſt loſt his life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amphiabel</hi> thy conſecrated ſeruant was ſlaine for thy ſake: <hi>Iulius</hi> &amp; <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> with many more.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Saxons</hi> inuaded with fire and ſword: thou laiedſt not aſide the care of thy land.</p>
            <p>But pittying that Infidels ſhould poſſeſſe the jewell: which thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17907:24"/>ſo well.</p>
            <p>Thou broughteſt to paſſe by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible wiſdome: that they alſo were by <hi>Gregory</hi> conuerted.</p>
            <p>Thus from the holy City, from <hi>Peters</hi> Seate: both the conquerour, and conquered receiued Religion.</p>
            <p>And being otherwiſe mortall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: yet in points of beliefe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in one.</p>
            <p>Neither did the <hi>Brittaine</hi> argue the <hi>Saxon</hi> of hereſie: or reproach him to haue receiued an vpſtart and falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied faith.</p>
            <p>As likewiſe, neither did the <hi>Dane</hi> chaunge the <hi>Saxons</hi> beliefe: nor the victorious <hi>Norman</hi> bring in newe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions.</p>
            <p>For they found no other: then all Chriſtendome at that time profeſſed.</p>
            <p>Of the faith Catholike, vvhich in this Iſland: thou (O eternal truth) hadeſt in this wiſe planted, watred, and eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:17907:24"/>
            <p> Who is able to comprehend the ſucceſſe? what tongue can expreſſe the encreaſe?</p>
            <p>All quarters of the earth talked of her fruit: all corners of this Realme teſtifie it.</p>
            <p>So many Churches &amp; Chappels ſo many Colledges and Hoſpitals: ſo many ſundry foundations of charity.</p>
            <p>So many thouſandes of vowed Religious: among whome night nor day, thy prayſes neuer ceaſſed.</p>
            <p>Who ſpent their time in praying for their Country: putting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues as a wall betweene thy wrath, and the people.</p>
            <p>Watching, vvhilſt others ſlept: liuing in penance, whilſt others paſt their time in pleaſures.</p>
            <p>No Country yealded more Kings Canonized for their liues: or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs by their deaths.</p>
            <p>More that viſited in Pilgrimage: the Temples and Monuments of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17907:25"/>chiefe Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>More Princes which laying aſide their Crowne and Scepter: in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious habite and Cloiſters, finiſhed their age.</p>
            <p>Or more Queenes, and Kinges Daughters: who renouncing world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pompe, choſe Chriſt for their Spouſe.</p>
            <p>Holy Biſhops in whome thy hart was well pleaſed, were very many: ſome of which loſt their liues for their flocke.</p>
            <p>Thou hadſt here alſo Eremites &amp; Anchorets many: equall in perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Fathers of <hi>Aegipt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both ſanctity and wiſdome thou didſt powre aboundantly: vpon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thy ſeruantes.</p>
            <p>This Iſle as a nource of learning: ſent teachers into ſtraunge landes.</p>
            <p>As a Seminary of Religion: it did ſpread abroade the Chriſtian faith.</p>
            <p>No Country but boaſteth of ſome
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17907:25"/>
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> Saint: honouring his reliques, whoſe life they had in admiration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Germany</hi> acknowledgeth from <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> her firſt Apoſtles, and Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes.</p>
            <p>Who founded there thy faith, O Lord: by word, workes, and by their bloud.</p>
            <p>By one of our nation: were the <hi>Noruegians</hi> reclaymed from their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions.</p>
            <p>And the froſen nations of the North-pole: beganne to be enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with thy loue.</p>
            <p>Our Kinges alſo in honour of thy ſacred name: and in ſigne of perfect vnion to thy Church;</p>
            <p>Offered vp their proteſtation of obedient Children: and made the Realme tributary to <hi>Peters</hi> chaire.</p>
            <p>They erected a Colledge at <hi>Rome</hi> thy holy City: that from whence their faith firſt proceeded, it might ſtill be conſerued.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:17907:26"/>
            <p> The deuotion of all to thy holy and dreadfull Sacrifices: it is not my tongue, thou knoweſt, can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe.</p>
            <p>It vvas thou vvhich gaueſt them both ability and will to crect ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtately Temples, with towres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring to the cloudes.</p>
            <p>To adorne the ſame with ſuch rich furniture: Croſſes, Chalices, and ſhrines of pretious mettall.</p>
            <p>So that neither ſparing labour nor coſt: they left examples of deuotion to all poſterity.</p>
            <p>Religious zeale being well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in all mens hartes: other fruits of good life followed accordingly.</p>
            <p>The vine yealdeth not Scamony: the Pomegranate beareth not Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quintida.</p>
            <p>Neither could good Doctrine: bring forth euill fruits.</p>
            <p>It delighted thee to looke vpon this Realme: and to regard the ſtate
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17907:26"/>thereof.</p>
            <p>To ſee howe parentes loued their children, more to thee then to the world: more by reaſon then fond affection.</p>
            <p>Howe children obeyed their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, not to the eye only, but from the hart: not for their owne behoofe, but for thy commaundement.</p>
            <p>Howe Maſters to their ſeruants, ſeruants to their Maſters: the Prince to the people, the people to the Prince.</p>
            <p>Each obſerued to other their duty inuiolable.</p>
            <p>The Clergy to the laity: the laity toward the Clergy.</p>
            <p>Howe all Superiors to their Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors bare themſelues vpright: and receiued likevviſe of them their due.</p>
            <p>Howe each man had juſt care of his ſoule: and fewe gaue themſelues ouer to iniquity.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:17907:27"/>
            <p> How ſinners haſtned by penance and teares: to reconcile themſelues to thy mercifull Majeſty.</p>
            <p>All thinges went in order, and the ſweet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſort of the common wealth: was as the harmony of a wel-tuned inſtrument.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="Psalm">
            <head>A DEPLORATION OF <hi>THE REVOLT OF EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> from the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>faith.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">THE FOVRTH PSALME.</head>
            <p>MY God, O my God; O God of our Aunceſtors: vvhere is the goodly tree of thy planting become?</p>
            <p>Which proſpered and grewe ſo mightily: which flouriſhed ſo beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully.</p>
            <p>Whoſe ſhade was moſt pleaſant
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17907:27"/>and recreatiue: whoſe armes ſtreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to the foure Seas.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cedars</hi> of <hi>Libanus</hi> vvere not taller; the <hi>Palmes</hi> of <hi>Paleſtina</hi> fairer: nor the <hi>Okes</hi> of the forreſt ſtronger.</p>
            <p>I heard of the glory and fame thereof, and I wondred: I looked about to ſee it, and it is not to be found.</p>
            <p>Alas, O Lord, that thou haſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a parching wind to blow from the <hi>North:</hi> which made the boughs thereof to wither, and the flouriſh thereof to decay.</p>
            <p>The leaues firſt fell away by one and by one: other followed by ten and by twenty.</p>
            <p>As when the Sunne draweth to his fartheſt point: and the cold nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping winter prepareth his recourſe.</p>
            <p>The ſmaller boughes beganne to fall to the ground: being become dry ſtickes without ſappe.</p>
            <p>The contagion at length poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17907:28"/>the hart: maine branches brake away.</p>
            <p>The trunke all rotten fell downe: the fall thereof was very great.</p>
            <p>The cracke vvas heard into all landes: and made Nations quake for feare.</p>
            <p>Peeuiſh ſhrubs, whome her ſhade oppreſſed: &amp; inferiour trees, whome her glory diſgraced;</p>
            <p>Such triumphed at her fall: and rejoyced at her ruine.</p>
            <p>But the other goodly trees of the wood, pittied her calamity: and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their owne eſtate.</p>
            <p>Yet juſt art thou, O judge of all the world: and there is no iniquity in thy wayes.</p>
            <p>Before thou didſt thus abaſe our Nation, they ſinned: and before thou didſt ſo chaſtiſe our Country, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the rodde.</p>
            <p>Our forefathers were vnmindfull of the multitude of thy mercies: and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17907:28"/>kept not the couenant of thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements.</p>
            <p>But beginning to vvauer at the noyſe of newe opinions: their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners drew infection from the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their faith.</p>
            <p>When they ſawe the theefe they followed him: to be partaker of his pray.</p>
            <p>They joyned ſhot with the adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous generation: &amp; furthered their proceedinges.</p>
            <p>And eating with vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: mingled themſelues with thoſe, which thou haſt ſtrictly forbidden.</p>
            <p>They learned their workes, they ſuckt in their opinions: and ſtumbled to their vtter ruine.</p>
            <p>They found in their conuerſation the ſcandall of <hi>Balam:</hi> eating &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and fornication.</p>
            <p>Thy <hi>Nazarites</hi> were prouoked to violate their vowes: and inuited to meates renounced.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:17907:29"/>
            <p> Way was by liberty made open to intruſion of a newe beliefe: and men vaunted their proper inuentions to be thy word.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed is the memory, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting is the glory of the ſhepherds: which looked well to their charge, at the time of Apoſtaſie.</p>
            <p>For the brightneſſe of <hi>Iſraell</hi> was not quite put out: but that many lampes gaue their accuſtomed light.</p>
            <p>Rather chooſing triumphantly to looſe their liues: then by yealding to betray their flocke.</p>
            <p>Curſed for euer are thoſe Prelates and Paſtors: not worthy the name of ſubjectes and ſheepe.</p>
            <p>Who either ſlept while the Diuell ſowed his cockle, O eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach! or like dumbe dogges bayed not when they ſawe the wolfe.</p>
            <p>Idols &amp; ſtockes, not truſty watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: who ſawe the ſword comming, and gaue no warning.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:17907:29"/>
            <p> But wonne with reward, or ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with feare: ſuffered ſoules to be ſeduced.</p>
            <p>The Prince frowning: and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding his lawes to be obſerued for Gods truth;</p>
            <p>They ſtaggered as men dronke: all their wiſdome and learning was gone with a word.</p>
            <p>Holding downe their heades as degenerate: &amp; ſhrinking as rammes that had loſt their hornes:</p>
            <p>In ſteede of denouncing to people their daunger: and deterring them from iniquity.</p>
            <p>They themſelues yealded GODS honour to man: and augmented the ſcandall by their example.</p>
            <p>Great was the multitude, which ſwaying with the time: did cut off themſelues from the body of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome.</p>
            <p>The earth vvas infected vvith the pride thereof: and the aire deteſted
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17907:30"/>ſo great abhomination.</p>
            <p>The elementes were defiled with continuall ſacrileges: the bloud of the Saintes cryed vengeance.</p>
            <p>Angry vvaſt thou vvith thoſe, which were once thy beloued peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and diſclaymedſt from <hi>England,</hi> as none of thine inheritance.</p>
            <p>Alſo deliueredſt vp therefore the faint-harted ſhepherdes, vvith their flockes: to the handes of their mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall enemies.</p>
            <p>Thy Sacrifice was taken from an vnworthy generation: thy Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies were aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>Vnder name of diuine ſeruice were obtruded newe rites: for thy Sonnes body, a bare peece of bread.</p>
            <p>The table and cup of Diuels, was thruſt vpon the people: with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereunto belonging.</p>
            <p>Blaſphemies &amp; hereſies were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed for Goſpell: and all mens mouths opened againſt heauen.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:17907:30"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>England,</hi> ah vngratefull <hi>England,</hi> forgate thee the liuing God: and felt the curſe of hauing a child to her King.</p>
            <p>Thus the bournes became de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert: and a batefull land turned to a ſoure ſoile.</p>
            <p>Catholike faith here firſt planted: vvhich neither <hi>Saxons</hi> altered, nor <hi>Dane</hi> aboliſhed;</p>
            <p>Which the <hi>Normans</hi> rejected not: which ſo many ages had not vvorne out;</p>
            <p>Was nowe at laſt in a moſt infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate age: corrupted, chaunged, &amp; deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>And our Nation after a thouſand of yeares, Apoſtated from thy faith: to the vvhich it vvas firſt conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Yet remembring thy former mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: thou didſt diſſolue at laſt this heauy yoake.</p>
            <p>Sending a <hi>Debora,</hi> vvhich judged
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17907:31"/>
               <hi>Iſraell</hi> in peace and tranquillity: and repared the late ruines.</p>
            <p>But too ſoone thou tookeſt her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: for the vnworthineſſe of her ſubjectes.</p>
            <p>Quickly was thy goodneſſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: the Realme returning to her vomit.</p>
            <p>Thou pouredſt forth therefore thine indignation in aboundance: &amp; kindledſt all thy wrath to the full.</p>
            <p>Thou gaueſt vs ouer to our owne inuentions: ſuffering vs vvith full ſaile to make our courſe.</p>
            <p>Our ſinnes deſerued no leſſe: yet vvhat could thy vvrath doe more extreame?</p>
            <p>The Nobility to their owne vtter extirpation: ſhamefully forſooke their Biſhops without aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Who conſtantly in defence of the Church: pined all in durance and periſhed one by one.</p>
            <p>The common ſort went vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17907:31"/>to the golden Calues: and at the commaunders voice, bowed their knees to <hi>Baall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sincere Chriſtians fled from <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon:</hi> leaſt they ſhould be plunged in her iniquities.</p>
            <p>Thou determinedſt in thy wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fury: to caſt of <hi>England</hi> for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>To let it runne to the bottomeleſſe pit: and neuer to recall it to the faith.</p>
            <p>But a <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſtood vp before thee: entreating for his comfortleſſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
            <p>Appeaſing thy wrath, thou ſaidſt vnto him: prepare thy ſelfe to be my inſtrument.</p>
            <p>For I will reare vp a newe genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of Prieſtes and people.</p>
            <p>They vvhich ſo eaſily forſooke me in time of tentation: ſhall not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the land of promiſe.</p>
            <p>Forthwith didſt thou puruey in a ſtraunge lande: a receptacle for thy
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17907:32"/>people, a refuge for thy perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Chooſing out ſuch as it pleaſed thee: of whome to frame veſſels of honour.</p>
            <p>Many thou drewſt to thy ſeruice: by whome the Diuell wiſhed to ſet forth his owne glory.</p>
            <p>As diligent bees they gathered hony in aboundance: for ſuccour of their diſtreſſed Country.</p>
            <p>Being deliuered like <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of the fornace of <hi>Aegipt:</hi> and called like <hi>Abraham</hi> from houſe and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>Thou inſpiredſt them vvith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of conuerting ſoules: and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt them in due ſeaſon of thy har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt.</p>
            <p>Vnder banner of a ſecond <hi>Gregory:</hi> they aduentured the ſecond conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Nation.</p>
            <p>Oppoſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the ſtreame of the time: hope againſt hope was
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17907:32"/>their comfort.</p>
            <p>As thou gaueſt them learning, which their aduerſaries can not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt: ſo conſtancy, which they can not ouercome.</p>
            <p>They purchaſed ſoules by their Doctrine: and confirmed them by ſeale of their bloud.</p>
            <p>Springes of health were opened: &amp; from all coaſtes men ſought helpe of their maladies.</p>
            <p>The cauſe waxed famous: men beganne to lift vp their eyes, and flowe to the Church apace.</p>
            <p>Sound of the Catholike faith, pearced through the Iſland: and none can anie more pleade igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p>Darkneſſe ſtroue to repell light: not able to endure the glimps there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>The Diuell armed himſelfe with furie to maintayne his KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOME: feelinge the foundation
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17907:33"/>thereof to tremble.</p>
            <p>Rigourous lawes were made: and executed with all extreamity.</p>
            <p>Worſe and worſe daylie added: ſeuerity finding neither end, nor meaſure.</p>
            <p>In theſe tearmes of contradiction (O ineffable Majeſty) ſtandeth thou ſeeſt, our miſerable <hi>Britany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who by this time (hadſt thou not ſent ſupply) had become worſe then <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iniquity hath ingendred impiety: and want of faith, hath brought forth double iniquity.</p>
            <p>Ah thou eldeſt Daughter of <hi>Sion:</hi> howe is thy beauty faded?</p>
            <p>Howe miſerable is nowe the land: wont to be ſo happy and fortunate?</p>
            <p>The Lady of Iſles is become like a perilous rocke: which farre and neere is ſhunned for danger of ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke.</p>
            <p>Or as a curſed quick-ſand: infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17907:33"/>through deſtruction of many paſſengers ſwallowed.</p>
            <p>The chiefe of Prouinces is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the baſeſt: the moſt Religious, turned to moſt ſacrilegious.</p>
            <p>Woe to a ſinnefull people: whoſe burden is iniquity.</p>
            <p>Woe to an Apoſtatrice nation: who like an Harlot hath broaken her faith.</p>
            <p>From the crowne of the head to the ſole of the foote: ſhee is full of ſores and maladies.</p>
            <p>Who is able to cure her leproſie: and to remedy her loathſomeneſſe?</p>
            <p>She is proued a baſtard vine: and degenerated to a ſoure grape.</p>
            <p>A froward bowe, which will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flie in peeces: then come to the bent.</p>
            <p>A fruitleſſe and barren ſoile: not anſwerable to the ſowers hope.</p>
            <p>Againſt thee her God, ſhe hath lifted vp her hand: againſt the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17907:34"/>ſhe hath vaunted her fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>With a proude gate, and lofty countenance, ſhe hath ſtalked againſt thee: as though ſhe would checke thee to thy face.</p>
            <p>She ſaith I am ſafe, in the mideſt of waters: my ſhippes are my braſen wall.</p>
            <p>Yet is ſhe fleſh, and not a ſpirit: a worme and not a God.</p>
            <p>Be it that ſhe ſoareth as high as an Eagle: ſhee ſhould be reached with thy arrowe: but ſpare her, O Lord.</p>
            <p>Be it ſhe were as ſtronge as ſteele, ſhee ſhould bee daſhed in peeces by thy fury: but mittigate thy wrath.</p>
            <p>She extolleth her ſelfe in conceipt of proſperity: and vannteth her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedinges in iniquity.</p>
            <p>In a moment canſt thou cruſh her bones: and lay her pride in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17907:34"/>the duſt: but, oh remember thy mercy.</p>
            <p>VVhat-ſoeuer this people thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, is meere iniquity: all their communication, is conſpiracy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt heauen, and treaſon againſt thee.</p>
            <p>They haue all made a league with death: and concluded a couenant with hell.</p>
            <p>Their feete are ſvvifte to euill: and their handes ſtronge to doe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</p>
            <p>The earth it ſelfe is infected with wickedneſſe of the inhabitants: and cryeth vnto thee for vengeance.</p>
            <p>And poſsibly vvould ſvvallovve them, as it did <hi>Chore</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: vvere it not for thy elect ſake.</p>
            <p>Reuenging fire of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrha,</hi> might be juſtly feared: if the faithfull ſtayed not thy rodde.</p>
            <p>If any forſake iniquity, he is made
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17907:35"/>a pray: our chanels flow with bloud.</p>
            <p>Who did euer heare ſuch horrible thinges: as this people commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee their maker?</p>
            <p>Degenerated is thy vineyarde and turned wilde: yealding verjuce for wine.</p>
            <p>Thy darling and vowed Virgin: hath giuen ouer her ſelfe, common to all adulteries.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin</hi> ſhe hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened her boſome: and to whome ſo-euer elſe, that would diſhonour her.</p>
            <p>She hath ſought her louers farre and neere: and hired teachers for her itching eares.</p>
            <p>She careth not whome ſhe admit, ſo ſhe admit not thee her firſt ſpouſe: nor whither ſhe runne, ſo ſhe flie from thy face.</p>
            <p>As a woman contemneth her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſo hath ſhe contemned thee: and with diſdaine turned her backe.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:17907:35"/>
            <p> Defending her iniquity vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of thy glory: ſhe dareth to ſay; I am no adultereſſe, I am no Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatrice.</p>
            <p>Her braſen face cannot bluſh: her impudent minde can conceiue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>But if ſhe harden her face not to repent: harden the face of thy meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers to reprehend.</p>
            <p>If ſhe harden her face to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute: harden thou their face to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
            <p>Confirme the hartes of thoſe thy labourers: endue them with ſtrength from aboue, and giue ſucceſſe vnto their endeauours.</p>
            <p>Whoſe only preſence repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in ſome ſort: the ſtate of former times.</p>
            <p>And maintayneth thy holy fire: that it goe not out.</p>
            <p>Diminiſh not their number, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our ſinnes, and vnworthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17907:36"/>but encreaſe it for our better comfort.</p>
            <p>That the daylie foode of our ſoules we may receiue at their hands: and not want their aſsiſtance in our extreamities.</p>
            <p>Protect them night and day from their enemies: whereſoeuer thy bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines detayneth them.</p>
            <p>Embolden our harts with courage from heauen: to concurre with them freely in furthering thy ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Fully thereby to diſcharge our Chriſtian duty: and be partaker of their reward and Crowne.</p>
            <p>So may they build apace the wales of thy <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> and winne innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable ſoules to thy Kingdome.</p>
            <p>So may they ſpeedily bring to paſſe: that auncient happineſſe may returne.</p>
            <p>So may thy Temples be clenſed of their abhominations: returning to the vſe whereunto they were buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:17907:36"/>
            <p> No longer be dennes of Diuels: and inſtruments of thy diſhonour.</p>
            <p>Be it ſo, O mighty Patron of thy afflicted: be it ſo.</p>
            <p>And all that loue their Country: let this be their daylie teares.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="Psalm">
            <head>A CONTEMPLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION <hi>OF THE BLES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> ſtate of a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">THE FIPT PSALME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>OME and conſider vvith me the ſweetneſſe of our Lord: O all yee, that be of his holy congregation. Come and conſider with me the glory of his Spouſe: O all yee, that dwell in her Tabernacle.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:17907:37"/>
            <p> Come and conſider with me the happineſſe of your owne ſoules: yee which haue entred into the ſanctuary of our God.</p>
            <p>Meditate his goodnes in the night: &amp; in the day time lift vp your handes vnto his holy Seate.</p>
            <p>Great is he, and vvorthy of all prayſe: thy workes beare witneſſe of thee, O Lord.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt erected thy Church, as thy Kingdome vpon earth: her glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall not depart from the lippes of thy Saintes.</p>
            <p>In thy only Sonne it was founded from the beginning: and to the end of the world it ſhall endure.</p>
            <p>For faithfull art thou in all thy wordes: and holy in all thy workes.</p>
            <p>Iuſt &amp; righteous in all thy wayes: and perfect in thy determinations.</p>
            <p>As in the ſunne-beames, thou haſt placed this thy Tabernacle: that the vertue thereof might comfort the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17907:37"/>world.</p>
            <p>Vpon an hill thou haſt ſituated thy City: whither all people ſhould repaire for lawes, and doctrine.</p>
            <p>This is the Queene ſtanding at thy right hand: glittering in gold, and rich attire.</p>
            <p>Thy Spouſe, vvhome thou canſt not, but loue: thy turtle, which can not, but be chaſt and true.</p>
            <p>The piller of truth: whereupon thy faith is builded.</p>
            <p>The rocke, againſt vvhich hell gates ſhall not preuaile.</p>
            <p>The ſhip which thou permitteſt to be toſſed: but neuer ſuffereſt to be ouerwhelmed.</p>
            <p>The arke ordayned to ſaue the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: out of which who ſo is found, periſheth euerlaſtingly.</p>
            <p>The ſanctuary of refuge: whither to flie from the anger to come.</p>
            <p>The mount of thy ſanctification: which the right hand hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:17907:38"/>
            <p> The inheritance, which thou haſt purchaſed with thy Sonnes bloud.</p>
            <p>A pauilion immoueable: vvhoſe pinnes can neuer bee pulled out, whoſe cordes can neuer be broaken.</p>
            <p>A high and ſtrong Caſtle, vvhoſe vvalles are Adamant: againſt which no ſtrength can preuaile.</p>
            <p>A maſſy &amp; hard ſtone: vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whome it lighteth, it cruſheth him in peeces.</p>
            <p>All benediction thou haſt beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon thy Church: vvho hath not her for Mother, ſhall not haue thee for Father.</p>
            <p>In her only thou haſt eſtabliſhed thy true worſhip: and confirmed it neuer to faile.</p>
            <p>As other people haue Gods: none the true God but Chriſtians:</p>
            <p>So may factions adore the alſo: none truly and fruitfully, but thy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church alone.</p>
            <p>Among all trees thou haſt choſen one Palme: amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g al birds one Doue.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:17907:38"/>
            <p> Among all flowres thou haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred one Lilly: among all hilles one <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All nations are thy ſubjectes and creatures: but we thine inheritance.</p>
            <p>Rejoyce and be glad, yee inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> among whome is the great and holy one of <hi>Iſraell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yee are all like Gods: the true children of the Higheſt.</p>
            <p>Happy are the eyes, vvhich ſee that yee ſee: and enjoy the preſence of him, whome yee adore</p>
            <p>Happy are the eares, that heare, what yee heare: and the harts, which are partakers of your inſtructions.</p>
            <p>No nation vnder heauen hath a God ſo potent, ſo louing: ſo neere to them, which worſhip him.</p>
            <p>More pretious are your ſoules in his ſight: then the Phoenix or the Vnicornes fole.</p>
            <p>He hath raiſed vnto you a ſeate of mercy: whither to haue recourſe
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:17907:39"/>for remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And prepared a table for your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: wherein himſelfe is the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet and feaſt.</p>
            <p>O howe delectable are thy dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, O Lord? howe acceptable are thy holy Altars?</p>
            <p>Much better are the reliques there of: then the exquiſite cates of princes.</p>
            <p>Much better is it to be an abject in thy houſhold: then a great man in Kings Courtes.</p>
            <p>The meaneſt in thy Church is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: the pooreſt in thy Church is rich.</p>
            <p>Who is able to expreſſe the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence of thy Church: or the one halfe of her glory?</p>
            <p>We haue Prieſtes rightly conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated: and anointed in ſacred wiſe.</p>
            <p>Orderly accompliſhing thy dread full miſteries: in veſtments of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and honour.</p>
            <p>Monkes, and other Religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17907:39"/>perſiſting day and night in prayer.</p>
            <p>With faſting and diſciplines affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting themſelues: in ſackcloath and hayre for the ſinnes of the people.</p>
            <p>Vowed Virgins, veiled hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maides of thy Chriſt: by like order of life contend for like Crowne.</p>
            <p>And fixing him profoundly in hart: whome they haue choſen as celeſtiall Spouſe.</p>
            <p>Endeauour nothing elſe, then to be perfect in his ſight: and ſerue him without diſtraction.</p>
            <p>Vpon the ſociety of thy faithfull: legions of Angels attend for their defence.</p>
            <p>Vpon them thy eyes are perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually open: to conſider their wants, and heare their prayers.</p>
            <p>Who liueth in their vnity, is in the communion of Saintes: partaker of their aſſiſtance and patronage.</p>
            <p>Hath his part in euery good deed:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:17907:40"/>and is daylie prayd for, throughout the world.</p>
            <p>Who dieth a liuely member of this holy body miſticall: by prayers of the liuing hath remiſſion of payne.</p>
            <p>Happy art thou, O flocke of <hi>Peter:</hi> bleſſed are all nations, ſubject to his chaire.</p>
            <p>Where ſit the judges of the houſe of <hi>Iacob:</hi> the rodde and ſcepter of thy Kingdome, O Redeemer.</p>
            <p>Thy ſelfe art a watchman ouer it, who neuer ſleepeſt: a protector, who neuer ſlumbreſt.</p>
            <p>Whoſoeuer impugne it ſhall rotte as they liue: their eyes ſhall ſinke, and their tongue ſhall be eaten out.</p>
            <p>They ſhall periſh in thy fury: and melt like waxe before the fire.</p>
            <p>None ſhall reſiſt thy Church, and be innocent.</p>
            <p>No man fighteth againſt her with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out foile: he daſheth his fiſt againſt a Rocke.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:17907:40"/>
            <p> Her enemies ſhall licke the duſt of her feete: and thoſe which oppugned her, kiſſe her ſteps.</p>
            <p>Such as will not, ſhall be called a reprobate company: vvith vvhome thou wilt exerciſe eternall wrath.</p>
            <p>Aboundance of bleſſinges vpon all them, which honour her: and curſes eternally will followe them, which vexe her.</p>
            <p>Her loue and mercy is more: then the tender hart of a Mother.</p>
            <p>Her anger more to be feared: then a Princes rage.</p>
            <p>In her remayneth knowledge, vvhich can not erre: power, vvhich may not be contradicted.</p>
            <p>In her is the treaſure of thy Sons merits repoſed.</p>
            <p>In her poſſeſſion are the Keyes of thy heauenly Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Thou art her teacher: that ſhee may not be ignorant.</p>
            <p>The holy Ghoſt is her ſanctifier:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:17907:41"/>to preſerue her from iniquity.</p>
            <p>As the Moone from the Sunne fetcheth her light: ſo is ſhe illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from Chriſt her Spouſe.</p>
            <p>In her only doſt thou raigne with magnificence: in her only thou art to be found.</p>
            <p>Not ſo the Sinagogue of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: not ſo the congregation of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes.</p>
            <p>Among whome, as in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſitteth the Prince of pride: who hath dominion ouer all children of darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Preſuming as though they were thy counſailors: or as if the holy Ghoſt ſpake in their eare.</p>
            <p>As though they were the lampes of the world: with whome Religion was borne, &amp; with whome it ſhould die.</p>
            <p>They ſay to the auncient Fathers, hold your peace: and to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church, we will teach
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:17907:41"/>you wiſedome.</p>
            <p>But their pride is more then their power: for thou dwelleſt not in harts ſubject to ſinfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>Swelling in cogitations of their harts: they proudly toſſe vp their heddes, as vntamed coltes.</p>
            <p>As childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Belial</hi> without yoke: they challenge liberty without obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>Prieſtes they make to themſelues for their newe lawe: and put vpon them authority, which they cannot giue.</p>
            <p>Like Apoſtata children they haue made aſſemblies, &amp; not in thy name: begonne a webbe, and not in thy ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Falſe Prophets ſell them follies and lies: and ſet cuſhions of eaſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſinners elbowes.</p>
            <p>For a little lucre they juſtifie the wicked: vpon confidence of faith, they aſſure ſaluation.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:17907:42"/>
            <p> Peoples ſores they cloſe vvith a falſe skinne: vvhen the vvound fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth, they ſay all is well.</p>
            <p>Eating in effect the peoples ſinnes: and cloathing themſelues vvith their iniquities.</p>
            <p>In ſteede of the ſuperſubſtantiall Bread of life, they giue them Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents: for the Chalice of ſaluation, poyſon of Adders.</p>
            <p>Making thee more vnjuſt then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Tyrant: they teach that thou pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheſt all ſinnes with equall payne.</p>
            <p>And that vvithout difference of deſertes: thou rewardeſt all vvith e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall glory.</p>
            <p>They ſay thou canſt not make thy Saints and Angels, to vnderſtand our prayers: nor ſhewe to them thinges done in earth.</p>
            <p>They fooliſhly ſay that thou wilt not haue vs honour thy friendes: and that thou ſetteſt litle by their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:17907:42"/>
            <p> Denying that vvhoſe ſinnes the Church forgiueth, are forgiuen in heauen: they ſay thou canſt not giue ſuch authority to man.</p>
            <p>Doubting of thy Omnipotency, they ſay with the <hi>Capharnaits:</hi> howe can Chriſt giue vs his body for food?</p>
            <p>With the faithleſſe they ſticke not to ſay: his wordes are hard, and who can beleeue him?</p>
            <p>His promiſe of being vvith his Church to the end of the vvorld: they contemne.</p>
            <p>And that the Holy Ghoſt ſhall teach her all truth they credit not.</p>
            <p>Wanting the band of vnity: vnder, ſeuerall heades, they make ſeuerall companies, and ſects.</p>
            <p>Hauing no certayne rule of faith, each is author of his owne beliefe: framing a Religion by priuate fancy.</p>
            <p>Both in Doctrine and life, all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order is among them: eternall hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and confuſion.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:17907:43"/>
            <p> Oh with how great difference (moſt ſupereminent light) haſt thou ſeperated <hi>Iſraell</hi> from the <hi>Aegyptians?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So plaine haſt thou made the high way of truth: that a very foole neede not miſſe the path.</p>
            <p>Our enemies giue teſtimony to our faith: and confeſſe that we may be ſaued therein.</p>
            <p>They which oppugne it doe juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it: in confeſsing the primitiue Doctors to haue erred with vs.</p>
            <p>And thy Church not vnmindefull of her great priuiledge: nor vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for thy benefits.</p>
            <p>Honoureth thee alwaies with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward purity, worthy of thy holines: and with outward ornaments, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of thy Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Seauen times in the day ſhee ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth thy prayſes: and prayeth for Catholikes throughout the world.</p>
            <p>Heare her prayers (O enemy of falſhood) and giue all the earth to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:17907:43"/>vnderſtand;</p>
            <p>That Hereſie is a tempeſt raging only for a time: but the foundation of thy Church endureth for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="Psalm">
            <head>A PSALME, WHEREIN <hi>THE CATHOLIKE CAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth</hi> to minde his conuerſion, giuing thankes to God <hi>for the ſame.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">THE SIXT PSALME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>EDITATE, O my ſoule, a newe ſong: open my lips to a pſalme of thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</p>
            <p>Rejoyce in him that made thee: rejoyce in him that redeemed thee.</p>
            <p>Rejoyce in him that conſerueth thee: rejoyce in him that ſanctifieth thee.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:17907:44"/>
            <p> Rejoyce in thy Lord, thy God: rejoyce in thy King, and Captayne.</p>
            <p>He hath delighted in thee, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thee: and exalted thee to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Lifted vp thy head: and awaked thee from ſleepe of death.</p>
            <p>Broaken thy bondes aſunder, and ſet thee at liberty: that thou ſhouldſt liue acceptably before him, in the land of the liuing.</p>
            <p>VVhilſt thou walkedſt peruerſe paths, he regarding thy miſery: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined better of thee, then thou didſt deſerue.</p>
            <p>From thee, not ceaſſing to offend him daylie, hee turned avvay his anger: and kindled not all his wrath.</p>
            <p>His eye of pitie hee fixed vpon thee: when thou wert vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull of him.</p>
            <p>By ſecreet and ſundry meanes: he drewe thee to his ſeruice.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:17907:44"/>
            <p> Cleane he hath wiped thee from al filth: placed thee in a faire way, and bid thee walke therein.</p>
            <p>As the potter frameth his veſſell, or the jueller poliſheth his pretious ſtone: ſo laboured he thee, to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purpoſe.</p>
            <p>By open examples: by priuie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations.</p>
            <p>By threats and allurements, by proſperity and aduerſity: he ceaſſed not to call thee.</p>
            <p>Aproach therefore, O yee, which feare our Lord: herken what great mercy hee hath performed in my ſoule.</p>
            <p>I will ſing vnto him for his abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant clemency: I vvill prayſe the name of the Higheſt.</p>
            <p>He who from a-loft, watreth the hilles with ſweete ſhowres: that the earth may bring forth her encreaſe;</p>
            <p>Hath refreſhed my barraine ſoule with heauenly dewes of grace: that it
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:17907:45"/>may waxe fruitfull to righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Hee who prouideth wherewith the beaſtes of the deſert may quench their thirſt:</p>
            <p>Hath not ſuffered my ſoule: to periſh in a deſolate lande.</p>
            <p>He which neaſteth the birdes in trees, and fowles in the rockes: hath placed me in the tree of his owne planting, and in the rocke of his owne foundation.</p>
            <p>Thou gaueſt me knowledge, O my God, to ſeeke remiſsion of ſins: and inckling to flie from the wrath to come.</p>
            <p>As the day-ſtarre ariſing from the Eaſt: thou ſhalt chaſe darknes from my hart.</p>
            <p>I heard thy voyce as a whiſpering in mine eare, and trembled thereat: I felt thy knocking, as of one deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be let in.</p>
            <p>So had I often donne before, but ſtill was obſtinate: exaſperating too
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:17907:45"/>too much thy long patience.</p>
            <p>Pardon me, O Lord, that I was ſo dull to heare thee: pardon me, and I will redeeme thoſe dayes with great diligence.</p>
            <p>Pardon me, for thou knoweſt we are fleſh and bloud: prone to euill, and ſlowe to piety.</p>
            <p>At laſt thou calledſt me with an effectuall voice: and I anſwered, I am ready.</p>
            <p>For why thou kneweſt what was fitteſt to mooue me: and gaueſt me thy hand to helpe me vp.</p>
            <p>I caſt off my former damnable ſloath: and ſet forward my feete to the pathes of peace.</p>
            <p>I ſaide to my ſelfe, hie thee O wreatch, into the houſe of God: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lappe of his holy Spouſe.</p>
            <p>I reſolued to take no repaſt, nor enter into the bed of my repoſe: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till my ſoule were made the Temple of the Holy ghoſt.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:17907:46"/>
            <p> Vntill ſhee had made her peace with the Almighty: and were purged of her iniquities;</p>
            <p>Wherby endued with grace I might ſecurely go to reſt: &amp; ſleep in ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
            <p>I bowed my knees, and lifting vp my handes: humbly beſought thee, Author of all goodneſſe;</p>
            <p>Happily to accompliſh the worke which thou hadſt begone in me: and to ſet me in ſtate of grace.</p>
            <p>Thou heardſt my prayer: and I atchieued the juſt deſire of my hart.</p>
            <p>I ſought earneſtly to finde one of thine anointed: for diſcharge of my conſcience.</p>
            <p>One of thoſe vvhome thou haſt choſen: and ſent to guide people to thy Kingdome.</p>
            <p>To whome Chriſt bequeathed the exerciſe of his function: as he before had receiued it of his Father.</p>
            <p>To vvhome hee gaue the Holy Ghoſt: promiſing that in forgiuing or looſing ſinners, their judgement
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:17907:46"/>he would ratifie.</p>
            <p>In vvhome hee hath placed the word of reconciliation: and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of his holy Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Sending them as Embaſſadors to declare his will: and commaunding to receiue them as repreſenters of his owne perſon.</p>
            <p>Hard was it for me to finde ſuch one of thy ſeruants: for the dayes of <hi>Elias</hi> are returned, when the Prophets were hidden in caues.</p>
            <p>Yet thou gaueſt me fauour in the ſight of thy <hi>Sunamite:</hi> I was admitted to ſpeech of the heauenly Phyſician.</p>
            <p>Embracing his ſpirituall exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: in ſolitarynes I began to prepare.</p>
            <p>I ſate downe &amp; ſtreightly exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my ſoule: as he, which is to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der account of moſt weighty matters.</p>
            <p>Our aduerſary the Diuel ſtood on my left ſide, and ſaid: wilt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe thy ſecrets to a ſinnefull man?</p>
            <p>I anſwered, auant <hi>Satan,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made me impudent to ſinne:
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:17907:47"/>ſuggeſteſt ſhame of repentance.</p>
            <p>He wiſhed me to differ till a fitter time: and ſaid, there was no haſt.</p>
            <p>But conſidering howe long I had prouoked thy patience: I feared by ſodain ſummos of death, to be taught vnprouided.</p>
            <p>He propoſed danger of the lawe: I replied, that God was to be obeyed before Princes.</p>
            <p>He objected that the Lord only forgiueth ſinnes: I anſwered, that from him only I expected remiſſion, but by miniſtery of man.</p>
            <p>As likewiſe in thy name (O migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of mightieſt) Phyſitions heale, and thy Saintes worke miracles, thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the author of both.</p>
            <p>I letted not therefore to diſcloſe my ſinnes to thy ſeruant: that I might of him receiue abſolution, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile.</p>
            <p>I diſcouered euen my moſt ſecret ſores, as to a skilfull Chirurgion: and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:17907:47"/>obtayned with health, holſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiues.</p>
            <p>Recounting my ſinnes in the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of my ſoule: I accuſed my ſelfe with my owne lippes.</p>
            <p>I ſorrowed for all, knowing that thou wilt not be ſerued by halues: and that thou accepteſt not him, which renounceth not euery ſinne.</p>
            <p>I confeſſed all: knowing that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is he, who lieth to the holy ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Abhominable is a diſſembler in thy Sacraments: &amp; his fruit as of him, who layeth venime to his wound.</p>
            <p>Or thinketh to be eaſed of his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: vvhen he fooliſhly addeth a mighty weight to his backe.</p>
            <p>I ouercame ſhame, and endured to bluſh: that in the world to come I might not be confounded.</p>
            <p>But, oh howe ſoone did I receiue the reward of my labour: vvho can expreſſe the ſweetneſſe that I found in my ſoule?</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:17907:48"/>
            <p> I taſted of thy dainties (O Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne ſweetneſſe) vvhich thou haſt reſerued for them, which feare thee.</p>
            <p>The excellency whereof none can imagin: but they only which proue it.</p>
            <p>A droppe (as it were) I felt of the celeſtiall fountayne: wherewith thou bleſſeſt thy Saints and Angels.</p>
            <p>A teſtimony of thy inuiſible grace; a ſeale of the remiſſion of my ſinnes: a pledge of eternall glory.</p>
            <p>When ſhall the memory of that time be renewed: by experiment of like joy?</p>
            <p>Which while I taſted I could hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger nothing elſe, then righteouſnes: nor thirſt any thing, but the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</p>
            <p>I ſaid boldly, come death nowe when thou wilt: I haue vnburdned my ſoule, and am ready.</p>
            <p>Flie <hi>Satan,</hi> I renounce thee for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: thou haſt no part in me at all.</p>
            <p>The bloud of our LORD hath
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:17907:48"/>waſhed me: and the merit of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hath made me hole.</p>
            <p>Nowe finde I them lyers, which ſlaundered our holy Mother: terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying me from her Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>Sects haue a ſhadowe and name of Religion: not like thy lawe, O Lord.</p>
            <p>I found thy faith to be vnſpotted: without ſtayne of any folly.</p>
            <p>Conuerting ſoules from their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wayes: and giuing wiſdome to the ignorant.</p>
            <p>Pearcing to the very hart: and comfortable to a ſingle ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Quickly was my deſolation tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to joy: thou claddedſt me vvith conſolation, as with a robe.</p>
            <p>Nowe therefore being redeemed by my Maker: from the hands of the enemy;</p>
            <p>I confeſſe that he is gentle, good, and exceeding bountifull: and his mercy endureth for euer.</p>
            <p>I ſate in darkneſſe, and in the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:17907:49"/>ſhadowe of death: and there vvas none to helpe me.</p>
            <p>I cried vnto him, &amp; he ayded me: breaking my fetters in ſunder.</p>
            <p>Had he not aſſiſted me: the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had euen ſwallowed me quicke.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be his holy name: vvho gaue me not for a pray to the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons jawes.</p>
            <p>As a litle bird I eſcaped the fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers net: as the ſilly hare from the purſuing gray-hound.</p>
            <p>By the old aduerſary of mankinde I had beene ſeduced: and ſupplanted by his malice.</p>
            <p>My God ſtreatched out his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent hand: deliuering me from the violent ſtreame.</p>
            <p>Who caught me in his armes, as if a father ſhould catch his child: from the deuouring beare.</p>
            <p>Becauſe he loued me, he ſought my ſaluation: not ſuffering the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to triumph.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:17907:49"/>
            <p> Prayſe him therefore, O my ſoule: be not vngratefull for his benefits.</p>
            <p>Forget not what he hath done for thee: preuenting thee in his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges.</p>
            <p>He hath made thee flouriſh afreſh: as in the yeares of thy firſt regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Reſtoring thy innocency againe: and renewing thy youth as an Eagle.</p>
            <p>As farre as heauen is from earth, or <hi>Eaſt</hi> from <hi>Weſt:</hi> ſo farre hath he remooued from thee thine iniquities.</p>
            <p>He hath crowned thee with better then pretious ſtones: all parts and povvers vvithin mee, magnifie his mercy.</p>
            <p>I ſtaggered in attempting my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: the difficulties of the time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed me.</p>
            <p>Thou girdedſt me with vertue: &amp; vnder thy protection I ouercame thoſe tentations.</p>
            <p>I was ſlowe and weake, thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:17907:50"/>me ſwift like an Hart: that I ran forwardes without impediment.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt taught me to fight ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully againſt the enemy: and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med my hart to be thy champion.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt raiſed me from vvorſe then the dunghill: and placed me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt thy holy, &amp; princely people.</p>
            <p>Out of the lake of miſery thou haſt pulled me: and from the dirty dregs of ſinne, &amp; hereſie, thou haſt drawne me forth.</p>
            <p>From Deaths dore thou reuiuedſt me: from Hel-gates thou broughteſt me backe.</p>
            <p>Oft to the barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſendeſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: to me an orphane thou gaueſt thy Spouſe for a Mother.</p>
            <p>Many vvonderfull thinges thou bring eſt to paſſe: none more ſtrange doe I knowe, then the conuerſion of my hard hart.</p>
            <p>Many wayes thy mercy ſheweth it ſelfe: but neuer more then in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:17907:50"/>my offences.</p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſay, O Lord? thou haſt engraffed thy name in my hart: and enroled my name in thy booke of life.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt ſhrowded mee in thy tabernacle: againſt the day of wrath;</p>
            <p>Opening to me the gates: where none but the juſt enter.</p>
            <p>In vaine haue the fiends like foxes ſought my ſoule: departing voide of their expectation.</p>
            <p>I will loue thee therefore, O my aide and refuge: my ſtrength, and the foundation of my hope.</p>
            <p>The new tune which thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to my mouth: I wil alwayes ſing.</p>
            <p>I will offer before thy Altar a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of prayſe: in the ſight of thy Angels &amp; Saints I will giue thankes.</p>
            <p>The cup of thy Croſſe I will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect: deſiring to ſuffer for thy ſake.</p>
            <p>What other way can I be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to thy giftes? or how can I doe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:17907:51"/>this alſo, except thou giue it.</p>
            <p>Thou needeſt neither me, nor my good deedes: thou haſt choſen me, and not I thee, O Redeemer.</p>
            <p>My conuerſion vvas thy handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke: without whoſe aſſiſtance I can not thinke a good thought.</p>
            <p>Who am I, O Fountayne of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: that thou thus ſhouldeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt thy ſelfe vnto me?</p>
            <p>That ſuffering thouſandes to wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe ſtill in wickedneſſe: thou cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt me on whome to ſhewe mercy.</p>
            <p>Neither tookeſt me out of this life in time of blindneſſe: in mideſt of mine iniquities.</p>
            <p>To thy ſelfe, O Lord, to thy ſelfe: bee the glory of this thy mercifull kindneſſe.</p>
            <p>Let the heauens prayſe thee for it: and in earth others be conuerted by my example.</p>
            <p>Let my daylie endeauours be to further thy faith: and drawe others
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:17907:51"/>to the delectable ſpring, wherewith my ſelfe haue beene refreſhed.</p>
            <p>So ſhall thy graces in ſome ſort re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to thee againe: as floodes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the Sea.</p>
            <p>So ſhall I not periſh like an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull tree: which leaueth not his like behinde.</p>
            <p>Prayſe yee meane-ſpace, your Creator and mine, O yee his Angels: who rejoyce at conuerſion of euery ſinner.</p>
            <p>Who perpetually execute his wil: without declining at any time from his heſts.</p>
            <p>Prayſe yee him, O his holy Prieſts: meſſengers of his will, ſhepherdes of his folde: by whoſe handes he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileth ſinners.</p>
            <p>Prayſe yee him, O al yee my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: partakers of like ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Whome of caytiues plunged in like errours: he hath juſtified, and made righteous.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:17907:52"/>
            <p> Prayſe yee him, O all his ſeruants: neuer yet entangled with like miſery.</p>
            <p>Prayſe him, O my ſoule, whilſt thou quickneſt my body: when thou parteſt by death, ceaſſe not to doe the ſame.</p>
            <p>And when thou receiueſt the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againe: prayſe him perfectly without end.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="Psalm">
            <head>AN IMPLORATION <hi>OF DIVINE GRACE,</hi> againſt temptations of <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">THE SEAVENTH PSALME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOV taughteſt me perfect wiſdome in my firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, O Lord: and I verily truſted neuer more
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:17907:52"/>to be ſhaken.</p>
            <p>In the day of her reconciliation, thou ſaidſt vnto my ſoule: nowe art thou my faire Spouſe, this day haue I aſſumed thee.</p>
            <p>Why then doth the tempter whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper in my eare, and ſay: hovve long vvilt thou ſerue thy GOD in vaine?</p>
            <p>Why doe the ſpeeches of thoſe mooue my minde: who ſaying they loue me well, vpbraide me to my face of follie.</p>
            <p>Objecting that I ſpend my age in wilfull calamity: neither reape the pleaſure of my life.</p>
            <p>Remember, O Lord, the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table word: that thou ſpakeſt to my hart.</p>
            <p>Preſerue me ſtill among the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which ſeeketh thee: which alone enjoyeth thy preſence &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
            <p>Which with vndefiled lippes and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:17907:53"/>cleane hart, offer vp day lie ſacrifices: and magnifie thy holy name.</p>
            <p>Among whome only, is ſaluation to be hoped for: and thy true honour to be found.</p>
            <p>Let mee alwayes put my truſt in thee: and neuer be aſhamed of the God of my forefathers;</p>
            <p>Nor deny my ſelfe: to be of his holy choſen company.</p>
            <p>Keepe me, O my maker; that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in thought, word, or deede: I conſent to rites of a ſtraunge Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or partake in their actions.</p>
            <p>Neither openly, nor priuily, in ſpeech nor ſilence: by action nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, or any ſigne whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Leaſt I bee enwrapped in their plagues, becauſe of their company: and drinke the cup of their damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Let neither friendſhip, nor hatred: profit nor loſſe;</p>
            <p>Payne nor pleaſure, life nor death:
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:17907:53"/>ſeparate me from thy Church.</p>
            <p>Suffer not that my brethren, and fellowe ſeruants: ſtumble by my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, to their ruine;</p>
            <p>Or ſay of me; ſee howe he hath loſt his part in <hi>Iſraell:</hi> his inheritance aboue the ſtarres.</p>
            <p>Loe howe he was not built vpon a rocke, but vpon ſand: great and ſhamefull is his fall.</p>
            <p>Permit not that my ghoſtly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſcorne at me, and point me out: this is he, whoſe ſoule we haue ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
            <p>Who beganne a worke, and could not finiſh it: ſatisfying our eyes with his diſgrace.</p>
            <p>Let not the aduerſaries of thy law and teſtament: triumph ouer me as of a conqueſt.</p>
            <p>Conceiuing by my example that more will yeald: and fewe reſiſt a cruell aſſault.</p>
            <p>And that we eſteeme no more of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:17907:54"/>our faith, then they of theirs: nor haue aſſured certainty of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>Forbidde the fowles of the ayre, the fiendes of hell: to take from my hart the ſeede, which thou haſt ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en.</p>
            <p>Forbidde that either riches and cares choke it: or the heate of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution wither it.</p>
            <p>Forbidde that perſwaſions of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall friends ſhould corrupt it: or any thing elſe hinder the encreaſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>Fie, that wealth ſhould be dearer to me, then my faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or worldlie friendes, then my God.</p>
            <p>Heretofore I comforted other: and when I am touched my ſelfe, ſhall I tremble?</p>
            <p>Where is then my awe and loue? where is ſortitude and patience?</p>
            <p>Where is the dutie of a Chriſtian man become?</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:17907:54"/>
            <p> The conſtancie and ſeruice, which I owe to thee my GOD, I vvill alwaies keepe: to thee my life ſhall liue.</p>
            <p>The word of truth take not out of my mouth: for in thee is all my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.</p>
            <p>Curſed are they: which decline from thy Commandements.</p>
            <p>All iniquity therefore bee farre from me: ſtill may I cleaue to thy lawe.</p>
            <p>Dilate my hart, comfort my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: that I may cheerefully runne my race, and gayne my crowne.</p>
            <p>Shall I not loue thee: whome on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I ought to ſerue?</p>
            <p>Shall I joyne with thy enemies: in their prouocations and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies?</p>
            <p>Or ſhall I lie with my lippes, and ſay I loue thee: when I doe not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe thee?</p>
            <p>No, no, I vvill confeſſe thy
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:17907:55"/>Religion: neither before people, or Magiſtrate will I be aſhamed.</p>
            <p>Leaſt thou deny me likewiſe at the latter day: and before thy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Saints, put me to confuſion.</p>
            <p>If they vrge me with obedience: I will not let to tell them, that God muſt be obeyed before man.</p>
            <p>If they threaten paynes: I will ſet before mine eyes the euerlaſting tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, prepared for rennegats.</p>
            <p>I will tell them, that whatſoeuer they can doe: muſt haue a ſhort end.</p>
            <p>Happy man, who eſcapeth paines: which neuer ceaſe.</p>
            <p>If they puniſh me, I will with thy Apoſtles rejoyce: that thou haſt vouchſafed me, to ſuffer for thy ſake.</p>
            <p>If they kill me, it is the vtmoſt of their power: and the beginning of my glory.</p>
            <p>Yet know I that <hi>Satan</hi> is chayned: and can not hurt a hayre, but by thy permiſſion.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:17907:55"/>
            <p> Thou art my light, and my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whome ſhould I feare? thou art my protector, whereat ſhould I quake?</p>
            <p>Heauen fall; the earth ſinke: the whole frame of the world turne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide downe;</p>
            <p>All that is therein runne to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion: chaunce vvhatſoeuer may chaunce;</p>
            <p>Rather then that I forſake my faith: by renouncing to be of thy holy congregation.</p>
            <p>One thing only is neceſſary, O my Lord, and my God: to ſerue thee ſtedfaſtly; and all thinges elſe are vaine.</p>
            <p>In this happy courſe begonne: graunt that I faint not, during my life.</p>
            <p>The zeale which thou once didſt in me kindle: ſuffer not to waxe cold.</p>
            <p>Let not the ſpirit of thy loue: be in me extinguiſhed.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:17907:56"/>
            <p> Though I forſake all for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious pearle: which thou haſt reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto the world:</p>
            <p>Yea though I forſake my ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: I buy it not too deare.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt ſhewed me a hidden treaſure: the price of the field, I muſt, and will pay.</p>
            <p>This only with <hi>Dauid</hi> I aske of thy diuine Majeſty: to dwell in thy houſe all the dayes of my life.</p>
            <p>To be a member of thy holy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy myſticall: a childe of thy Spouſe for euer.</p>
            <p>That I may be partaker: of thy perpetuall Sacrifice;</p>
            <p>Whereby thy Paſsion is applyed vnto vs: and we reape the fruit of our redemption.</p>
            <p>Giue me thy grace, O thou which ſanctifieſt ſoules: giue me ſtrength and courage, giue me wiſdome and patience.</p>
            <p>Then, though a thouſand fall on
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:17907:56"/>my right ſide, and ten thouſand on my left: yet will I ſtand.</p>
            <p>Though thoſe, which ſhine like the Sunne and Moone, fall from thy kingdome: yet will I be ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt.</p>
            <p>Thou forſakeſt none, except they firſt forſake thee: confirme there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my heart, that it may neuer quaile</p>
            <p>Confidence in mine owne power I haue none: but what is it that in thee, I dare not vndertake?</p>
            <p>In thee, who art the mightieſt, haue I placed my hope: thou art my refuge, to thee I commend my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt deliuer mee from the open arrovve by day: and from darke daungers of ſecret malice.</p>
            <p>From the Day-diuell, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations: vvhich comming in their ovvne likeneſſe, dare ſhewe their face.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:17907:57"/>
            <p> And from the night ſpirits: which ſhroude themſelues vnder faire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences.</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer become of me, to thy bleſſed will I reſigne vp my ſelfe: my fortune is in thy hand.</p>
            <p>Great, O Lord, art thou; great is thy might: and thy wiſdome is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible.</p>
            <p>Many perils our frailty is wont to fore-caſt: ſtill we cry, fearing to be drowned.</p>
            <p>But if we delight in thee thou wilt, thou wilt giue vs our deſires: and bring thoſe feares to nothing.</p>
            <p>Men will forge excuſes: to ſerue their turne.</p>
            <p>And a thouſand ſhiftes iniquity ſearcheth: to build vnto it ſelfe a ſinnefull, and falſe ſecurity.</p>
            <p>Thou ſearcheſt the harts &amp; peines: diſcerning eaſily howe men flatter themſelues.</p>
            <p>Shall I (as diuers doe) blind mine
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:17907:57"/>eyes, leaſt I ſhould ſee? or when I ſee, ſhall I not vnderſtand?</p>
            <p>Shall I ſeeke darkneſſe in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Sunne: and ſubject my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to my will?</p>
            <p>Direct my paths according to thy lawe: that vnrighteouſneſſe neuer ſubdue me.</p>
            <p>Regard my affliction and combat: diſpoſe of me according to thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence ouer the Elect.</p>
            <p>Keepe my feete from ſliding, and be ſtill before mine eyes: preſerue my ſoule from the death of deadly ſinne.</p>
            <p>For thoſe which ſo die inherit not with thee: but with them in whoſe ſeruice they partake.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt once lightned my la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe: keepe me therefore euermore from darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Examples ſometime doe giue me ſcandall: prouoking my hart in like ſort to ralent.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:17907:58"/>
            <p> Ah wreatch that I were: if I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied my ſoule vpon ſuch ſhattered reedes;</p>
            <p>And would (as it were) for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: poſt forward to hell.</p>
            <p>Whereas holy examples are plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull: of glorious Confeſſors, which fill the priſons.</p>
            <p>It hath come to my minde, that I may be ſaued at the laſt: and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent vvhen Death knocks at the doore.</p>
            <p>A foole, whoſoeuer ſo ventureth eternall damnation: not knowing hovve ſoone he ſhall be cited to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
            <p>Thy grace is not alwayes at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement: and vncertayne is the valewe of conſtrayned repentance.</p>
            <p>The tempter hath ſuggeſted that thou art mercifull: and wilt eaſily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough forgiue.</p>
            <p>But thy mercy and clemency I haue already prooued: in expecting
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:17907:58"/>me to ſaluation;</p>
            <p>In not ſtriking me in midſt of my ſinnes: and taking me away in mine ignorance.</p>
            <p>It is nowe time to thinke of thy judgementes: and hazard no more to prouoke thy wrath.</p>
            <p>Who aſſureſt vs that thou art a ſeuere Iudge: and compareſt thy ſelf to a ſoure Maſter.</p>
            <p>The vvilie Serpent hath put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my head: that the ſecret of my conſcience, I may to my ſelfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue.</p>
            <p>But thou commaundeſt not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble Religion: but preciſely to ſtand vpon profeſſion of a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</p>
            <p>He would make me beleeue that there is ſmall diuerſity: vvhereas their faith is blaſphemy, or ours Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</p>
            <p>The Diuell therefore once chaſed from my ſoule: neuer more may be
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:17907:59"/>returne to his former habitation.</p>
            <p>Hauing once ſet my hand to the plough: no more muſt I looke back, leaſt I become vnfit for thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>Being deliuered out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> I muſt no more minde it: but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the dreadfull example of <hi>Lots</hi> wife;</p>
            <p>Whome thou turnedſt into a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of falt: a perpetuall monument of an vnſtedfaſt, and vnſeaſoned hart.</p>
            <p>Saue me (O my Sauiour) from all ſuch vnſtableneſſe: that during my life, I may prayſe thee in thy houſe.</p>
            <p>Make me to flouriſh like a bay: within precincts of thy Court.</p>
            <p>Leaſt I wither in my prime: and enter quicke into hell-gates.</p>
            <p>Leaſt my latter ſinnes become more grieuous then the former: and my end worſe then my beginning.</p>
            <p>Nowe is the time of triall: nowe prooueſt thou my loyaltie.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:17907:59"/>
            <p> Our ſtate is a warrefare: and nowe is the houre of battaile.</p>
            <p>If I ſtreatch out my hande to a ſtraunge ſect: wilt thou not reuenge it vvith rigour?</p>
            <p>If I betray thee: ſhall I remayne vnpuniſhed?</p>
            <p>Stand ſtedfaſt in juſtice, O my ſoule: depart not from the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle and tents of thy God.</p>
            <p>Then may I with confidence ſhew my face: and not be afraid at the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible day.</p>
            <p>I ſhall depart this life in a good hope: my bones ſhall reſt in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>Litle it is that I can ſuffer for thy ſake, O bountifull King: and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſcourges the wicked themſelues ſuſtayne.</p>
            <p>My ſtorme ſhall paſſe: and when I ſeeme conſumed;</p>
            <p>At euening ſhall brightneſſe and felicity ariſe: as if the Sunne were at
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:17907:60"/>his higheſt.</p>
            <p>Vnder the ſhadowe of thy winge I will ſhrowde my ſelfe: vntill the dayes of deſolation be paſſed ouer.</p>
            <p>Obſeruing my profeſſion &amp; faith: my duety, purpoſe, promiſe, and allegeance vnto thee, O my God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="lamentations">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:17907:60"/>
            <head>FOVRE <hi>LAMENTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIONS, WHICH</hi> COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>POSFD IN THE HARD <hi>TIMES OF QVEENE ELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, may be vſed at all times, when the Church</hi> hapneth to be extreame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſecuted.</head>
            <div n="1" type="lamentation">
               <head>The firſt Lamentation.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EHOLD, Behold, O thou eternall eye, which neuer ſleepeſt: behold the daily vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations of thy faithful.</p>
               <p>See howe they are had in chaſe: and deuoured euery houre.</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:17907:61"/>
               <p> Regard how thy ſhippe is toſſed: &amp; conduct her to the haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of peace.</p>
               <p>The Seas ſwell, the skyes loure: the aire is cladde vvith dusky and griſly weedes.</p>
               <p>The waters lift vp their voice: the tempeſtuous billowes roare.</p>
               <p>The vvindes hideouſly torment our labouring barke: and all the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſeeme to conſpire our raine.</p>
               <p>Wicked fury houleth againſt vs, crying out: when ſhall they be pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vp by the rootes? vvhen ſhall their name periſh?</p>
               <p>All bowels of mercy are ſhut vp: and before our face they conſult vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our liues.</p>
               <p>Daylie doe the pangues of death diſcouer themſelues: we are as thoſe which expect their laſt houre.</p>
               <p>Our life hangeth by a ſmall thred: our feete are entring into the graue.</p>
               <p>We paſſe through fire and water, through nets and ſnares: and a-midſt
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:17907:61"/>the haunt of ſauage beaſtes.</p>
               <p>We muſt looke to our ſteps, as if we walked among Serpents: for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are they, which lie in wait to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy vs.</p>
               <p>Our dwelling is worſe then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Scorpions: and Cockatrice eyes lurke vnder euery couert.</p>
               <p>We lie open to accuſation of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſſolute vnthrift: to the injuries of euery froward companion.</p>
               <p>To the vnſatiablenes of euery co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetuous wreatch: to the violence of euery extortioner.</p>
               <p>Our backes are charged with tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations: and euery body ſittes on our toppe.</p>
               <p>Whoſoeuer wil pretend any thing againſt vs, hath eaſie audience: who claymeth any thing from vs, it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged his right.</p>
               <p>Our inheritaunces are giuen to ſtraungers: our poſſeſsions are rent and diſmembred.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:17907:62"/>
               <p> If we demaund juſtice, it is deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: it is anſwered that we be out of the lawes protection.</p>
               <p>Well it is, that wee bee not out of thine, O defendor of <hi>Iacob:</hi> O fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of orphans, and ſtaffe of widowes.</p>
               <p>Shadowe vs therefore vnder the winges of thy mercy: vntill the courſe of iniquity be at an end, and her tide at the higheſt.</p>
               <p>For our enemies haue aſſembled to purſue vs: that they may rauin our goodes, and liue of the ſpoyle.</p>
               <p>They fall vpon vs, as a Lyon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayting his pray: and as a Leopard lurking behinde a rocke.</p>
               <p>When they deuoure the innocent: they thinke his God ſhall not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it.</p>
               <p>With our bowels they glut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: forcing vs to yeald vp that, which we tooke from no man.</p>
               <p>Loſſe of our heritages, is the price of our piety: our patrimonies are
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:17907:62"/>taken from vs.</p>
               <p>Tabernacles of ſtrangers abound with our goods: and like houndes well fleſhed, they followe eagerly the game.</p>
               <p>As if this were nothing to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts: our perſons are alſo ſought to farther puniſhment.</p>
               <p>Purſuiuants are caſt off after vs, as grayhou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds after deere: or as the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauke is let fly at the ſilly partridge.</p>
               <p>By vngodly ribauldes our houſes are ranſacked: and that which ought to be to each man his caſtle, is no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity.</p>
               <p>What pleaſeth them, is their boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: whatſoeuer they lay hand vpon, is good purchaſe.</p>
               <p>We are haled forth of our dores: and brought before the Magiſtrate as malefactors.</p>
               <p>In whoſe preſence we are bayted at on euery ſide: each man by bitter taunts, either wreaking his ſpight,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:17907:63"/>or ſeeking credit.</p>
               <p>If any ſpeake faire, the poyſon of adders is moſt of all vnder his lippes: from venimous allurements deliuer vs, O Lord.</p>
               <p>Refuſing to doe againſt our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: we are tearmed Traytors.</p>
               <p>Diſturbers of the Realme: and obſtinate Rebelles.</p>
               <p>Our youngers deride vs: the vileſt among all the people laugh at vs.</p>
               <p>The fooliſheſt of them all, thinke them ſelues wiſe, beholding our caſe: and condemne vs of folly.</p>
               <p>Perſons vnworthy to liue, becauſe of their wickednes, to juſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: cry out at vs, as impious.</p>
               <p>The Iudges frowne: beholding vs with a terrible looke.</p>
               <p>The ſtanders by ſharpen their tongues againſt vs: and gnaſh their teeth.</p>
               <p>Intreating we are ſharply taken vp: ſpeaking reaſon in milde ſort, we
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:17907:63"/>are anſwered with rebukes &amp; curſes.</p>
               <p>Clamour of the baſeſt ſort haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth judgment: crying, Away with them, away with them.</p>
               <p>Much labour there is to finde vs guilty of crimes: with ſtrange que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions we are moleſted.</p>
               <p>By oath wee are vrged to accuſe our benefactors and brethren, yea our owne ſelues: &amp; are charged with thinges which we knowe not.</p>
               <p>Aduantage is taken of whatſoeuer we ſay falſe witneſſes depoſe againſt vs.</p>
               <p>Like wilde Bulles they puſh at vs with all their force: and open their mouthes like ramping Lyons.</p>
               <p>Malice barketh at vs on all ſides: and Enuie thruſteth out her ſting.</p>
               <p>Howſoeuer we anſwere, eſcape we cannot: except by yealding to their profeſsion, we deny thy faith.</p>
               <p>Some pittie our rebuke and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe: but none ſtand by vs in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:17907:64"/>
               <p> Some fauour vs inwardly: but dare not ſpeake in our behalfe.</p>
               <p>Kindred and familiars are eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: the neareſt in friendſhip ſtand fartheſt off.</p>
               <p>Aloofe they behold our calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: as thoſe which ſafe on the land, ſee others ſuffer ſhipwracke.</p>
               <p>Had we ſtolne, ordinary fauour might be found: appeached of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, we might be ſuccoured:</p>
               <p>But now for our conſcience vvee finde no mercy: neither can ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation finde grace.</p>
               <p>To priſon we are drawne: &amp; laid vp cloſe.</p>
               <p>Rods are made ready for vs: racks and other engins of torture are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</p>
               <p>He that eſcapeth beſt, lieth long forgotten: enduring the deſignments of his Keepers fury.</p>
               <p>Thus are we become like outcaſts
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:17907:64"/>of this world: like vile ragges, which are throwne out of dores.</p>
               <p>Euery day bringeth his load of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction: no place can recline our heades in ſafety.</p>
               <p>Comfort we haue none but only this: thou art on high, and in thy handes lieth the lotte of our fortune.</p>
               <p>We are brought exceeding lowe: as lowe as wormes of the earth.</p>
               <p>Vpon which paſſengers treade: and bigger creatures make their pray.</p>
               <p>Neyther haue wee at any time reſt: neyther finde we in any place ſecurity.</p>
               <p>If for a ſpace our Perſecutors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: it is to reenforce their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>If a calme ariſe in one place: the ſword rageth in many others vvith double ſeuerity.</p>
               <p>If they pretend any fauourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion: it is only in regard of far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:17907:65"/>policy.</p>
               <p>Who is yet free: can not warrant himſelfe any little vvhile from their fingers.</p>
               <p>And who thinketh himſelf ſecure: is often times in moſt daunger.</p>
               <p>The day layeth vs open: the night can giue vs no aſſurance.</p>
               <p>At home we are caught by ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: in the wayes we are apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by watches.</p>
               <p>Falſe brethren are mingled among vs: and by fayned friendes we are oft betrayed.</p>
               <p>No wit is equall to the malice of our foes: hardly can any fore-ſight fruſtrate their diligence.</p>
               <p>No not their ſinfull ſubtilty, who ſeldome ſeeke thy gratious Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: more truſting their ovvne policy, then thy diuine prouidence.</p>
               <p>In this wiſe while priſons are fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with thy ſeruants: or that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they are had in purſuit.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:17907:65"/>
               <p> Families runne to ruine: and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren want neceſſary education.</p>
               <p>Of this fathers feele in their harts the griefe: and mothers doe often complayne.</p>
               <p>But better is thy grace then great wealth: and a cleane ſoule then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite learning.</p>
               <p>To this and all other tribulations: giue an end, O bleſſed Father of heauen.</p>
               <p>Ioyfully that we may ſerue thee: in holyneſſe, and piety; in peace, and ſecurity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="lamentation">
               <head>The ſecond Lamentation.</head>
               <p>WHY number we our tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall detrime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, O moſt boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lord: which are the leaſt part of our preſent calamity:</p>
               <p>And lament not rather our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall loſſes: the diminiſhing of thy glory?</p>
               <p>Not our priuate damages: not our
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:17907:66"/>earthly diſcommodities, ſo much vexe and torment vs.</p>
               <p>But the zeale of thy faith conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vs: thy diſhonour is the great coraſiue:</p>
               <p>Reproches againſt thy Religion wee repute as our owne: daylie they light vpon vs as a tempeſt of ſtones.</p>
               <p>We pine away to ſee thy lawe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: and die for griefe that thy ordinances are deſpiſed.</p>
               <p>Mourning to conſider the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darkneſſe ſo enlarged: and impiety ſo deepely rooted.</p>
               <p>In our captiuity we weep amaine: calling to minde the calamity of thy Church.</p>
               <p>For neither can we ſing thy notes: hauing loſt our Temple;</p>
               <p>Nor with worthy magnificence celebrate thy Myſteries: being ſo impoueriſhed and ſpoyled;</p>
               <p>Nor haue any harty gladneſſe: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:17907:66"/>abridged of thy moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Seruice.</p>
               <p>Becauſe of this our VIRGINE mourne: our young-men lament, our aged wring their handes.</p>
               <p>Our Prieſts girt with haire, offer Sacrifice: as in the dayes of <hi>Iudith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For why, our lightes are fewe in number: our ſolemne Seruice is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</p>
               <p>Organs &amp; muſicke are laid aſide: the melody of <hi>Sion</hi> is out of vſe.</p>
               <p>Our glory is in captiuity: our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments are in the enemies hand.</p>
               <p>Suſteinance of our ſoules is bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: from the conduits of ſaluation we are excluded.</p>
               <p>Pretious and rare in theſe dayes is thy worde: thy holies are ſeldome ſeene.</p>
               <p>No otherwiſe liue thy Prieſts with the reſt of thy ſeruants: then as in the time of <hi>Elias,</hi> when they were hidden in caues.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:17907:67"/>
               <p> They are put to ſilence, who would raiſe vp <hi>Iacob</hi> to remorſe: and conuert <hi>Iſraell</hi> from her Apoſtaſie.</p>
               <p>Few are left to inſtruct people in the way of juſtice: and teach wreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to ſhunne ſinne.</p>
               <p>With grones, people ſeeke the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſubſtantiall foode.</p>
               <p>Neither without danger of death: ſearch they ſpirituall refection.</p>
               <p>The pathes are beſet with enuious eyes: in paſſage to thy holy rites, our ſteps are watched.</p>
               <p>Little ones craue the bread which came from heauen: and there is none to giue it them.</p>
               <p>They which had ſometime the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall <hi>Manna</hi> at wil: die in the ſtreets for hunger.</p>
               <p>He which feedeth thereon, liueth for euer; and hee which doth not, can haue in him no life: yet is it taken from vs.</p>
               <p>Aboliſhed are Confirmation, and
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:17907:67"/>holy Chriſme: principall armour vnto Chriſtian conſtancie.</p>
               <p>The reuerent rites of Baptiſme: are quite rejected as vnprofitable.</p>
               <p>The Diuell rejoyceth that hee is not adjured: but may dwell in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants from their firſt natiuity.</p>
               <p>Matrimony is concluded to be a prophane bargaine: neither bleſsing nor grace belonging thereunto.</p>
               <p>Orders are none at all: where thy Prieſtes ſate enſtalled, raigne thoſe whoſe perſons are not ſacred.</p>
               <p>Blinde guides, vnfaithfull watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, dogges dumbe to the theefe, &amp; barking at the houſhold.</p>
               <p>Hirelinges they peele the woole: ſuffering the ſheepe to periſh.</p>
               <p>They runne, and were not ſent: take charge of ſoules, without vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>In at the windowe they came, and not at the dore: they cry, The Lord, the Lord, &amp; he ſpake not vnto them.</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:17907:68"/>
               <p> Worne out in priſon are al thy true Biſhops: no one is aliue to ſuſtayne thy flocke.</p>
               <p>Prophecies, miracles, and viſions are taken away: rarely reuealeſt thou the ſecrets of thy Kingdome.</p>
               <p>No publike Altar, incenſe, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: either reſembled or verified is the time of Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>Ah, howe are golden times turned to droſſe: our plate to pewter?</p>
               <p>To adore thee in ſpirit and truth is heynous: to be preſent at thy Altar is a grieuous penalty.</p>
               <p>To vnburden conſcience at feete of a ſpiritual father: is a matter of life.</p>
               <p>At the houre of death it ſelfe, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution is denied: the extreamity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth not to pardon.</p>
               <p>The holy Vnction ordayned for our better paſſage: is not permitted.</p>
               <p>So that without juſt preparation: vvee muſt enter combate vvith our deadly enemy.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:17907:68"/>
               <p> Bookes for edification and prayer are committed to the flame: what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſerueth vs to deuotion, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
               <p>If they finde thy holy Myſteries, they tread them vnder feete: the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture of thy glory is their pray.</p>
               <p>Ornaments and veſſelles conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to thy ſeruice, are prophaned to priuate vſes: as in the captiuity of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At monuments of thy Sonnes paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or repreſentation of thy Saints: they vpbraid vs with Gods, and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</p>
               <p>Defacing thy memories, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend thy honour: and blaſpheming thy friends, they alleadge thine owne Commaundement.</p>
               <p>Lighting vpon reliques, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile them: if they finde the memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of thy death about vs, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce vs Traytors.</p>
               <p>If they catch a Prieſt, a hundred
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:17907:69"/>
                  <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>egs</hi> are at hand: vvhich dare lay violent hand vpon thine anointed.</p>
               <p>Who concealeth the guide of his ſoule, is not <hi>Caeſars</hi> friend: <hi>Abdias</hi> is not innocent.</p>
               <p>If any deuout <hi>Sunamite</hi> harbour <hi>Elias:</hi> her offence is vnpardonable.</p>
               <p>Who reuerenceth the higheſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop: is a ſuppoſed enemy.</p>
               <p>Prohibited it is to aſcend vnto thy Holy hill: to receiue any inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from <hi>Sion:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſeeke expoſition of the lawe at <hi>Peters</hi> chaire: and direction from the piller of truth.</p>
               <p>Neither are we permitted to enter into the Arke, out of which is no ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: neither will they which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidde vs, enter themſelues.</p>
               <p>They preſſe vs continually to run with them towardes hell: and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence in ſhewe, that which we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt in hart.</p>
               <p>If they infatuate any man by faire
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:17907:69"/>wordes, or threats: they tread him vnder foote, as ſalt which hath loſt the ſauour.</p>
               <p>They triumph as of a conqueſt: and hang vp flags of victory;</p>
               <p>Glorying to finde a Catholike as cold as themſelues: and which will caſt behind him, the care of his ſoule.</p>
               <p>Not for exerciſe of our faith only are we thus afflicted: but for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation alſo we are deteſted.</p>
               <p>Vertue is accounted miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: all thinges are lawfull, except to liue well.</p>
               <p>Who waxeth ſober and graue: ſuſpected is he, to intend ſomewhat.</p>
               <p>He that in quaffing and gluttony is not forward: is hated as a back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward perſon.</p>
               <p>Giue any man great almes, dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med he is a corrupter of people: a ſolliciter of mens harts to his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>Our thoughts are examined: what
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:17907:70"/>greater miſchiefe could mans wit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent againſt vs.</p>
               <p>As if it were a ſmall matter: to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in words the ſupreame Paſtor</p>
               <p>An oath is adminiſtred of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe: and abjuring in conſcience his authority.</p>
               <p>In ſuch ſort are our hartes ſifted: yet are we ſcorned with freedome of faith, and that liberty of conſcience is not impeached.</p>
               <p>Vrged we are on al-ſides: and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed betweene ſtreightes, ſtand at the mercy of our armed enemy.</p>
               <p>Open thy armes, O God of our ſanctification: and receiue vs into thy boſome.</p>
               <p>Whither elſe to flie we haue not: neyther art thou farre from them, which call vpon thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="lamentation">
               <head>The third Lamentation.</head>
               <p>END our miſery (O Father of pupilles) or take vs vnto thee,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:17907:70"/>leaſt malice of the time ſubuert vs.</p>
               <p>Better it is to die: then to ſee the enormity, and deſolation of our Country.</p>
               <p>In euery corner wee heare thy name blaſphemed: conſtrayned to lay our hand vpon our mouthes.</p>
               <p>Reprehenſion is not endured: thy Angels are forbidden to denounce the truth.</p>
               <p>Commandement is giuen to thoſe which preach, to ſpeake plauſible things: and conformable to the time.</p>
               <p>The ſinner ſinneth and is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended: wicked men are magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their doinges.</p>
               <p>Godlineſſe is quite gone: piety hath taken her leaue.</p>
               <p>Baniſhed are truth and vertue: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to forraigne landes.</p>
               <p>All mouthes are full of leaſinges: guilefull lippes yealding the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of their double hartes.</p>
               <p>Euery head ſearcheth a pillowe to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:17907:71"/>his iniquity: and euery elbowe a cuſhion of eaſe;</p>
               <p>That without al remorſe they may ſwallowe ſinne as dainties: and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe in bloud as in a pleaſant bath.</p>
               <p>They winke, leaſt they ſhould ſee: and will needes beleeue what ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ſuggeſteth.</p>
               <p>Inſpirations are rejected as tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations: perſwaders to perfect Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, are condemned for ſeducers.</p>
               <p>Howe long wilt thou endure thy faith to be thus neglected: and thy holies to be prophaned?</p>
               <p>Thy Saints to be perſecuted: thy truth to be troden vnder foote?</p>
               <p>No perſecution like vnto our op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion: no griefe comparable vnto our ſorrowes.</p>
               <p>From the <hi>Eaſt</hi> to the <hi>West,</hi> ouer all the face of this earthly globe: no where is the Catholike faith ſo pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the Turks &amp; Saracens,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:17907:71"/>is greater liberty of Religion: the Moores and Infidels reſtrayne not Chriſtian rites, with ſuch ſeuerity.</p>
               <p>Since we deſerue not releaſe of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction: yet for thy owne glory, let thy name no longer be prophaned.</p>
               <p>See howe thy enemies haue ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out alarme: and thy profeſſed foes, lifted vp their hornes.</p>
               <p>Saying openly, roote we out the nation of the faithfull: that the name Catholike may be no more heard of.</p>
               <p>They haue inuaded thine inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: as it were with fire &amp; ſword.</p>
               <p>Polluted thy Tabernacle with their abhominations: contaminated thy ſanctuary.</p>
               <p>Thy Churches are pulled downe: with the ruines whereof are built vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy pallaces of pride.</p>
               <p>Thoſe vvhich ſtand, either ſerue for euery vile office: or are worſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed to the table, cup, and ſeruice of Diuels.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:17907:72"/>
               <p> Such poſſeſſe the temple as ſhould be ſcourged forth: and whome thou forbadeſt to ſet foot within thy gates.</p>
               <p>Men haue there placed their owne ſignes, in ſteede of thine: and for thy Sacraments, their owne inuentions.</p>
               <p>Tranſlating thy glory to their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition: thy ſolemnities &amp; feaſts to the Idoll of their owne imagination.</p>
               <p>Houſes of prayer are dennes of theeues: places ſanctified are become abhominable.</p>
               <p>From whence the ſweetincenſe of deuotion aſcended to heauen: ariſeth now the ſtench of the bottomles pit.</p>
               <p>Where Angels ſung &amp; freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted: the Diuels nowe daunce &amp; triumph.</p>
               <p>For a newe faith is ſet vp againſt the auncient beliefe: a newe table and ſeruice, in defiance of thy holy Altar and Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>Thy high ſteward is quite reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: they ſay, we will not heare his voice.</p>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:17907:72"/>
               <p> If he call vs home we will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: if he commaund vs, we vvill runne farther off.</p>
               <p>Let vs breake the bands of his law: and caſt off his yoke from our necke.</p>
               <p>The bands, O Lord, of thy religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue caſt of, which were ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant: &amp; thy yoke which was ſo ſweet.</p>
               <p>They haue left thee, the fountaine of life: and digged to themſelues pits, which beare no water.</p>
               <p>They haue ſetled their malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee: and contriue that, which they ſhall neuer accompliſh.</p>
               <p>The name yet of hereſie they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject from their ſect: and the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of it, they returne vpon vs.</p>
               <p>Lawes of the firſt Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they vſurpe and abuſe againſt the Church: ordayned by them for her defence.</p>
               <p>Their Superintendents cite vs, concerning our faith: as if they held the chaire, which can not erre.</p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:17907:73"/>
               <p> They excommunicate vs from their congregation: and banne vs in their malignant Synagogue.</p>
               <p>Whither to goe is to bee accurſed indeede: and worſe then to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a flaming fornace.</p>
               <p>As faſt as they curſe, thou wilt bleſſe: and our reward ſhall redound into our boſome.</p>
               <p>When they are diſpoſed, our life is their paſtime: in teſtimony of thy truth, we are daylie ſlaine.</p>
               <p>The Magiſtrate rageth on his bench: the Miniſters from their pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits clappe their hands.</p>
               <p>The people mutter againſt vs: &amp; <hi>Baals</hi> falſe Prophets as fire-brandes of miſchiefe, ſound to the ſlaughter.</p>
               <p>For our faith, we are as ſheepe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for the butchery: ſtreetes are dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with martyrdomes of thy Saints.</p>
               <p>Their fleſh is giuen for food to the fowles of the ayre: their bloud bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the earth, being ſhed like water.</p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:17907:73"/>
               <p> Ripped vp they are aliue: which to ſheepe &amp; oxen men abhor to doe.</p>
               <p>With bloudy gripe, are their trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and breathing bowels drawne forth:</p>
               <p>In moſt execrable ſort caſt into the fire: euen before their face.</p>
               <p>Their quarters, leaſt thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not ſee it playne enough, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the gates of euery Citie: and vpbraide thy patience.</p>
               <p>Their heades are rayſed on high: to the terrour of the ſimple.</p>
               <p>Serued thus are thy Prieſts, whom thou haſt giuen charge of: not to be once injuriouſly touched.</p>
               <p>The earth couereth not the bloud that is ſhedde: neither ſtoppeth the ayre the cry thereof.</p>
               <p>All the riuers of the valleys, nor al the ſhowres of heauen: are able to waſh away the ſtayne and ſhame.</p>
               <p>No ſope, nor ſcowring can clenſe the crime: no darkneſſe, nor death it
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:17907:74"/>ſelfe can hide it.</p>
               <p>No continuance of time, nor the age of the world: ſhall make it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</p>
               <p>Other nations heare of it, &amp; hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue it: becauſe ſuch cruelty hath ſcarſe ſeemed poſſible.</p>
               <p>Poſterity ſhall read of it and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: all generations to come ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the fact.</p>
               <p>Our Perſecutors owne iſſue ſhall bluſh: to heare the outragious actes of their aunceſtors.</p>
               <p>Barbarous death of innocentes is much: yet to miſreporte the cauſe augmenteth the deſpite.</p>
               <p>Refuſall to commit an act againſt conſcience, call they rebellion: not to deny the Catholike faith, they tearme felony and treaſon.</p>
               <p>Traytors indeed, ſuch as were thy choſen Apoſtles: when forbidden to preach the truth.</p>
               <p>Such as the Primitiue Chriſtians:
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:17907:74"/>when by Heathen ſtatutes impugned was Religion.</p>
               <p>Manifeſt is our guilt, and great is our offence: vvhen by going to Church all is pardoned.</p>
               <p>All this we endure for thy ſake, (O thou fountayne of grace) not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolting from thy beliefe.</p>
               <p>We haue not forſaken thee: leaſt we ſhould be forſaken of thee, at the laſt howre.</p>
               <p>Not denied thee before men: leaſt we ſhould be denied of thee, before thine Angels.</p>
               <p>Turne therefore vnto vs thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious countenance: wherewith thou cheereſt the world.</p>
               <p>Giue eare to our prayers: conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our complaint.</p>
               <p>Heare the voyce of thy Martirs bloud: or at leaſt wiſe, heare their ſupplication and interceſſion.</p>
               <p>Whome ſpoyled of their garment of fleſh: thou haſt clad with robes of
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:17907:75"/>immortality.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="lamentation">
               <head>The fourth Lamentation.</head>
               <p>THE garland of glory is fallen from our head: the beauty of thy City is defaced.</p>
               <p>O God, the beholder of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batte: be mindfull of our abaſement, vnder the heauy hand of thoſe which hate vs.</p>
               <p>We hope in thee: becauſe we haue knowne thee, &amp; profeſſed thy name.</p>
               <p>Thou exalteſt the humble: and regardeſt a contrite hart.</p>
               <p>Streatch out thy hand to our aide: for thou art the buckler and defence of <hi>Iſraell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Father of orphans, Husband of widowes: piller of the poore.</p>
               <p>Teach men, not to lift vp them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vpon earth againſt thee: and thy Saints.</p>
               <p>Let not the memory of thy affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted be laid aſide: forget not his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:17907:75"/>for euer.</p>
               <p>Cheere vp his juſt deſire: eaſe the mourning of his hart.</p>
               <p>Chaſtiſe vs no longer in thy rage: nor correct vs with indignation.</p>
               <p>Heale vs for we are bruiſed: haue mercy vpon vs, for we are brought exceeding lowe.</p>
               <p>In ſilence we expect thy long-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired conſolation.</p>
               <p>True it is that we deſerue more of thy rodde, then we feele: and before thine anger, we ſinned.</p>
               <p>If we ſinne, are our foes righteous? if <hi>Iacob</hi> offend, is <hi>Eſau</hi> innocent?</p>
               <p>If <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> pleaſe thee not: ſhall <hi>Babilon</hi> delight thee?</p>
               <p>Wilt thou euermore be angry, O Supreame Iudge? or canſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get mercy?</p>
               <p>Wilt thou ſerue this Realme: as thou haſt ſerued <hi>Afrike</hi> and <hi>Syria?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To let misbeliefe prepare the way to Infidelity: ſuffering to enter an
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:17907:76"/>eternall Apoſtaſie?</p>
               <p>Let not the name of thy Chriſt &amp; Church be exiled: let not a faithleſſe generation roote vs out.</p>
               <p>Not ſo, O Lord, for thy tender kindneſſe and mercy: pull vs violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of cruell handes.</p>
               <p>Rouſe vp thy ſelfe like a Giant: reuenge the bloud of thy Saints.</p>
               <p>Let not the ſcourge of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: be alwayes vpon the backs of the juſt:</p>
               <p>Leaſt they preſume, ſaying, thou maintayneſt their cauſe: and that ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is on their ſide.</p>
               <p>Chaſtiſe vs with thine owne rod as children: and not with the rodde of the vncircumciſed.</p>
               <p>Pull the ſpeare out of the enemies reſt: knappe his launce in ſunder, and breake his ſword.</p>
               <p>Thou dwelleſt ſtill vvhere thou didſt: thou art the ſame God and glory of <hi>Iſraell.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:17907:76"/>
               <p> To thee our forefathers called op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by Heathen: and thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemedſt them.</p>
               <p>To thee Catholikes made their moane, vnder the yoke of <hi>Arrian</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes: and thou didſt redreſſe their bondage.</p>
               <p>So vtterly annihilating the aduerſe ſect: that ſcant their name remayned vpon earth.</p>
               <p>Euils innumerable compaſſe vs about: howe long wilt thou turne away thy face?</p>
               <p>Not for euer, O Lord: not for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, we beſeech thee.</p>
               <p>Shall ſo many ignorants, yet zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: neuer haue thy light reuealed?</p>
               <p>So many which for want of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction periſh: ſhall they neuer haue true teachers?</p>
               <p>Becauſe diuers which liued in the flouriſh of thy Church, haue ſet it at naught: ſhall thoſe neuer ſee it, who if they ſawe it would neuer forſake it?</p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:17907:77"/>
               <p> Becauſe many by yealding deſerue ſuch a yoke: ſhall they which are conſtant be alwaies vnder it?</p>
               <p>Shall the few ſparkles which thou haſt left in the lande: be extinguiſhed for lacke of cheriſhing?</p>
               <p>What if the fathers did eate a ſoure grape? ſhall the teeth of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for euer be on edge?</p>
               <p>The wicked wil not worſhip thee aright: ſhall they therefore be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vexed, which worſhip thee in ſpirit and truth?</p>
               <p>If thou haue decreed (O wiſdome incomprehenſible) concerning that generation, which enjoyed the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt glory of thy ſanctuary;</p>
               <p>And forſaking their Paſtors, ſtood not ſtedfaſtly for their Religion: in the time of contradiction;</p>
               <p>That they ſhal pine away by four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares trauaile in the deſert: &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enter into the land of promiſe:</p>
               <p>Nor ſee the glory of thy ſecond
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:17907:77"/>Temple: in all Royall magnificence:</p>
               <p>If this be thy holy pleaſure: &amp; the ſecret counſaile of thy long delayes:</p>
               <p>Or if the number of thy deſigned Martirs be not yet accompliſhed: to whome by theſe times, thou furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt a Crowne:</p>
               <p>Or if thou wilt needes haue the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of all harts to be opened: and rippe vp all diſſemblers, by long probation:</p>
               <p>That the vvhole vvorld vvorld may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, vvho ſerued thee from their hart: and who followe thee with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt intention:</p>
               <p>Or whatſoeuer elſe the depth of thy deſignments intendeth: by this ſo long perſecution:</p>
               <p>Yet haſten the times for thy deare mercy ſake: O liuing Lord.</p>
               <p>Calme the tempeſt, alay the rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wanes.</p>
               <p>Saue vs vvho are daungerouſly toſſed: vnite vs who are diſperſed,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:17907:78"/>and commaunded a-ſunder.</p>
               <p>That as one in hart, ſo with one voice in free aſſemblies we may laude thy holy name: &amp; extoll thy praiſes all the day long.</p>
               <p>Giue vs in the meane ſpace pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in our afflictions: and ghoſtly profit by theſe our temptations.</p>
               <p>Let them neither vvinne vs by vvordes, nor vveary vs by cruell deedes: O thou which art the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy people.</p>
               <p>Aide vs, O Sauiour: glorifie thy ſelfe in our deliuerance.</p>
               <p>Thou art the God of our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: thee only we will magnifie.</p>
               <p>Thou art a zealous God: we will not partake in thy diſhonour.</p>
               <p>Prepare the feete of thy forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: let vs heare the noiſe of their ſteps approching.</p>
               <p>Reueale the treaſures of thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: vvhich haue beene ſo long ſuppreſſed.</p>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:17907:78"/>
               <p> Graunt vs to reape at length with joy: who haue a great ſpace, ſowed in teares.</p>
               <p>In expectation whereof our life vaniſheth in griefe: our yeares con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume in ſobs;</p>
               <p>While we powre forth our ſoules before thee: crauing at thy handes ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Ariſe, O Lord, viſit thy flocke: raiſe vp the raſed walles of <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neglect not the vvaſting of thy heritage.</p>
               <p>Renewe thy truth, vvhich hath beene ſo long a time without fruit: let faith flouriſh againe like an oliue.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall all nations feare thy name: the Kings of the earth ſhall haue thy mercy in admiration.</p>
               <p>We ſhall all vvith one harmony ſing glory in thy Temple: and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie thy Altars with Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>All generations to come, ſhall prayſe thee: and make honourable
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:17907:79"/>mention of thy great goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>Thy Angels of heauen ſhall mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie thee: the Saints and bleſſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſhall fall at thy feete, and giue thankes.</p>
               <p>Euery ſoule pray that this may ſoone come to paſſe: and euery tongue ſay Amen.</p>
               <p>Come, O ſweete IESV, come.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:17907:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
